<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A refutation of the Apology for actors Diuided into three briefe treatises. Wherein is confuted and opposed all the chiefe groundes and arguments alleaged in defence of playes: and withall in each treatise is deciphered actors, 1. heathenish and diabolicall institution. 2. their ancient and moderne indignitie. 3. the wonderfull abuse of their impious qualitie. By I.G.</title>
            <author>I. G., fl. 1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103404</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839158</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839158</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3558</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02072)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3558)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1068:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A refutation of the Apology for actors Diuided into three briefe treatises. Wherein is confuted and opposed all the chiefe groundes and arguments alleaged in defence of playes: and withall in each treatise is deciphered actors, 1. heathenish and diabolicall institution. 2. their ancient and moderne indignitie. 3. the wonderfull abuse of their impious qualitie. By I.G.</title>
                  <author>I. G., fl. 1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 62 [i.e. 66] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By W. White, and are to be sold by Thomas Langley in Iuie lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.G. = John Greene.</note>
                  <note>The three points are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>An answer to: Heywood, Thomas.  An apology for actors.</note>
                  <note>P. 63-66 misnumbered 55, 58, 59, 62.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641. --  Apology for actors.</term>
               <term>Theater --  Moral and ethical aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Actors --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:3"/>
            <p>A REFVTATION of the Apology for ACTORS.</p>
            <p>Diuided into three briefe Treatiſes.</p>
            <p>Wherein is confuted and oppoſed all the chiefe Groundes and Arguments alleaged in defence of Playes: And withall in each-Treatiſe is deciphered Actors,
<list>
                  <item>1. Heatheniſh and Diabolicall inſtitution.</item>
                  <item>2. Their ancient and moderne indignitie.</item>
                  <item>3. The wonderfull abuſe of their impious qualitie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By I. G.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicero Officiorum lib. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Non ita a natura generati ſumus, vt ad ludum e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Iocum facti eſſe videamur; ſed ad ſeueritatem potius,</l>
               <l>Et ad quoedam ſtudia grauiora at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> maiora.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>W. White,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Langley</hi> in Iuie lane. 1615.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>A Refutation of the Apology for Actors</head>
               <head type="sub">And firſt, touching their Heatheniſh and Diabolicall inſtitution.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Mpietie is then growen to its full heigth, when it once preſumeth to boaſt of it ſelfe. <hi>Playes</hi> haue euer been condemned by godly Chriſtians; but now the impiety of <hi>Players</hi> is growen to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, that they take vpon them to defende their qualitie: And that which Wiſe and Good men haue euer repudiated for euill, they would haue vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and imprace for <hi>commodious</hi> good. Wherevpon one of them (amongſt the whole crew) hath publiſhed <hi>An Apologie for Actors:</hi> Which no ſooner it had preſented it ſelfe vnto my view, but in deriſion thereof I bought it, wondring in my minde, what <hi>M. Actor</hi> could ſay for himſelfe, to maintaine his idle Profeſsion. But when I had peruſ'd it, &amp; read it ouer, I conſidered, that thereby too too many credilous people might be ſeduced, and therefore a matter (in ſome ſort) worth the anſwering; and yet I perceiued ſuch ſlender aſſertions to be allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in defence thereof, that I deemed it not worth the anſwering by any graue <hi>Senior,</hi> or learned Clarke, but rather by ſome ſingle witted, and illiterat Pupill, that the victorie being gotten, might be the more glorious; and the ouerthrow giuen, the more ſhamefull and infamous.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3558:5"/>Wherefore I, although ranged amongſt the companie of ſuch vnlearned Nouices, and ſitting lag-tayle in the loweſt Fourme of their Shoole, haue notwithſtanding vndertaken to oppoſe and refute this <hi>Apologie,</hi> becauſe it doth not require a better Ingene then mine owne, to batter all the Bulwarks and Fortreſſes therein rayſed to oppugne the trueth, euer hitherto deliuered and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched againſt theſe <hi>Stagerites,</hi> and prophane ſpectacles preſented in the <hi>Theaters,</hi> to the as prophane ſights of all that goe to be ſpectators of them. Nor in thus doing, haue I entreated any to be a Patron and Protector of theſe vnripe Fruits of my weake vnderſtanding, againſt any the callumniations of thoſe that vndoubtedly I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to reſiſt my good intention (being ſuch onely as wallow in worldly pleaſure; or haue their mindes ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bound thereto) becauſe I know all good men, rightly religiouſly and ſinceerely diſpoſed, and all ſuch as with Reaſon ſhall weigh in the ballance of their ſound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what I haue written in this Booke will with emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſtriue, and if need be, contende who ſhall firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize my worke.</p>
               <p>And although <hi>M. Actor</hi> with all his complices and abettors, may condemne mee for an vnlearned Punie; and withall ſay, that I haue but <hi>Shot my Fooles Bolt at him:</hi> Yet I am perſwaded I ſhall not ſhoote in vaine, but at leaſt-wiſe wound, though I doe not kill: I meane, giue his <hi>Apologie</hi> ſuch a <hi>Blurre,</hi> that it ſhall not be able after neuer ſo much waſhing, to ſhew a cleane face againe. But in caſe he ſhall vpbraide me for my barbariſme and vnpoliſhed Phraſes voyde of all elegancie and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable ſtile, which throughout my whole Treatiſe I ſhall perforce vſe, being I was neuer ſchooled in the arts of Humanitie, nor practized in Rhethoricke &amp; Eloquence, it skills not; For I truſt not on him, but depende on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for the equitie of the cauſe I vndertake, knowing, that <hi>Tructh the more naked it appeares, the more comely it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3558:5"/>it ſelfe to all men, except her Aduerſaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now to vſe no longer, or more tedious prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, I will ſet downe the Method, I meaue to follow in my ſucceding Diſcourſe: Which is, Firſt to refute and oppoſe ſuch aſſertions wherewith <hi>M. Actor</hi> ſeemes to defend himſelfe: And afterward, to aduance the truth I take in hand; yea'uen in the ſame tripartit diuiſion, as himſelfe hath vſed in his <hi>Apologie.</hi> And ſo <hi>(ad remaggre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diar)</hi> to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Iehoue principium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD, who in the beginning, Created all thinges for his owne Glorie; and next himſelfe, for the ſeruice of Mankind, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other thinges hath Created many for the Recreation of mans wearied ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritcs, that after ſome refection, hee might the more dilengently and earneſtly apply himſelfe to the honeſt labours of his Calling. This benigne grace of the <hi>Almightie,</hi> men not content thankefully to accept of, nor moderatly to vſe, they haue vnthankfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and abuſed; turning the grace of God into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe: and in continuance of time by little and little, through <hi>Sathans</hi> meanes, haue deuiſed many vnlawfull artificiall Pleaſures, whereby they might paſſe away (as their name <hi>Paſtimes</hi> ſignifie) the moſt precious time of their life (which th'Apoſtle exhorts <hi>Warily to redeeme,</hi>) idlely and fruitleſſe, without any profite to the Church, or Common-wealth wherein they liue, or to their owne ſoules, which they ought heedfully to regard: But to the corruption of their Manners, drowning all Virtues in them, and choaking vp of the good <hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> which ſhould dwell plentifully in their heartes, and in ſtead thereof, ſowing the <hi>Tares</hi> reaped from vngodly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3558:6"/>and obſcaene <hi>Stage-playes,</hi> the moſt impious and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of all other vnlawfull artificiall Pleaſures. To the beholding of which, very many (more is the pitrie) <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi vi &amp; impetu coguntur,</hi> are by the prauitie of their nature, (addicted wholy to Pleaſures) carryed as it were with force and violence. Yea many of them in their heartes willing to conſume many Patrimonies, yearely ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding many poundes on theſe vaine repreſentations. By which meanes, the actors of them finde ſuch ſweete gaines to maintaine their idle life, that they giue their whole induſtrie to various and mimicall inuentions, that they might become <hi>Men-pleaſors,</hi> and thoſe moſt of the prophaneſt condition; and ſo conſequently diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of GOD. For noue can ſerue theſe two Maiſters to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, <hi>GOD and Belial.</hi> And now at laſt, by giuing two howers vaine Babling for as many howers gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Money, ſome of them become rich in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; and withall, proud to publiſh vnſauorie <hi>Apologies,</hi> for their impious <hi>Seminaries</hi> of euill Manners, (their <hi>Playes</hi> I meane, which breed ſuch euill effectes, as hereafter euery wheare ſhall be ſhewed) and withall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting them to the patronage of moſt Honorable peeres, thereby doubly to deceiue them whom they haue already ſeduced; That if ſuch a one protect it, Oh 'tis a worthy ſubiect, and to be imbraced (of them that hate goodneſſe) and who then dare contradict it? Yes aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly many thouſands, eſpecially of graue and reuerend Preachers of the Word, that hate their <hi>Playes</hi> for as bad Poyſon to the Minde, as the byting of a Viper to the Fleſh. Whom <hi>M. Actor</hi> in the ſecond line of his <hi>Apology</hi> moſt rudely calleth <hi>Seditious ſectiſts,</hi> hauing neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the vnitie which by application of the diuine Word they procure twixt man &amp; man, &amp; by their admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie betwixt God and man and his owne Conſcience, contrary to all ſedition in the world: Whom alſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, he giues foorth to be too <hi>Sower for Food, and too
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3558:6"/>rancke for Fodder.</hi> Happily becauſe hee, nor any of his fellowes can digeſt their good inſtructions and ſacred doctrines either as <hi>Food for men,</hi> or as <hi>Fodder</hi> for ſuch Beaſtes. But this firſt fault of his, may be pardoned, <hi>quia conſuetudo est altera natura</hi> becauſe that cuſtome of Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; Backbiting vpon the <hi>Stage</hi> with his tongue, hath brought him to vſe the ſame ſcurrility with his Pen.</p>
               <p>Afterwards followes, that the Princes of this Land amongſt other things haue tollerated certaine <hi>Theaters.</hi> Which is not to be denyed: but the Reaſon why, is to be enquired. For in like cafe is Vſurie, Dicing,<note place="margin">Why Playes are tollerated.</note> Sortile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, &amp;c. tollerated; yet none approoued and allowed. Any why then are <hi>Theaters</hi> tollerated? It is anſwered by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe vpon the like occaſion, in the Ghoſpell of S. <hi>Matthew;</hi> where being demaunded of the <hi>Phariſes, Why Moſes did commaund a man to giue a Bill of Diuorcement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth, 19.7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and put away his Wife?</hi> Hee anſwered: <hi>Moſes becauſe of the hardneſſe of your heartes, ſuffered you to put away your Wiues.</hi> And ſo Princes in theſe times, ſuffer (not allow) ſuch enormities, for the hardneſſe of their ſubiectes heartes; and for no other cauſes.</p>
               <p>Next enſueth his fayned dreame of the <hi>Muſe Melpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine;</hi> where by tooth and nay le he labours to ſhew what good the <hi>Muſe</hi> vſually effecteth. Which becauſe it tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the qualitie of <hi>Playes,</hi> I referre to conuince, till I enter vpon battering the Third part of his Treatiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will not wearie the Reader with too often repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, which I ſhall ſometimes be conſtrained vnto. Yet ſomethings therein hereafter not to be touched, may not be paſt ouer in ſilence. For after the <hi>Muſe</hi> had recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all her worth, and priſtine honour wherewith ſhee had been graced: Then peruerſely doth ſhe exclaime.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>But now's the Iron age, and Blackmouth'd Curres</l>
                  <l>Barke at the virtues of the former world.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Why this is the Iron age.</note>This age, is the Iron age indeed: and why? Becauſe the Magiſtrates throughout almoſt euery Cittie in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3558:7"/>Land, by their authoritie (repreſented in the Iron Sword borne before them <hi>Parcere ſubiectis, &amp; debellare ſuperbos</hi>) doe prohibite them from entring their precincts to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe their craftes. Whom if they admit, it's vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the great ſute made vnto them. Whereby the hardneſſe of the peoples heartes the more appeares, in that they ſtriue freely to giue acceſſe for ſinne to enter in and take poſſeſsion of them. Beſides, the honourable Citie of <hi>London</hi> hath ſpued them out from within her Walles, and reiected them to take vp their ſtanding in the Remoteſt places of the Suburbes, or no where elſe within her Iuriſdiction.</p>
               <p>Next, hath the <hi>Muſe,</hi> or rather <hi>M. Actor,</hi> again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred his former lycentiouſneſſe, impiouſly belching foorth blaſphemous words, calling reuerend Preachers, <hi>Blackmouth'd Curres:</hi> Becauſe,
<q>
                     <l>They tax the Vices of theſe preſent times,</l>
                     <l>Seeke to reclaime mens mindes i'gon aſtray,</l>
                     <l>Mis-ſpending precious time, to ſee a Play.</l>
                  </q>
Next.
<q>
                     <l>Some, whom for their baſeneſſe hist and ſcornd,</l>
                     <l>The Stage as lothſome hath long ſince ſpued out.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And how comes this to paſſe? But euen thus; Sinne leaues them: Why? becauſe they leaue Sinne. And ſo <hi>Playes</hi> leaue them, becauſe they leaue <hi>Playes.</hi> For further anſwere to which, I will recite this example. That the wiſe <hi>Cato</hi> once went into the <hi>Theater</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently departed foorth againe:<note place="margin">Cato.</note> and being demaunded why he did ſo; anſwered. <hi>He went into the Theater only that he might be ſeene and knowne to goe out of it.</hi> Now let all men iudge by this anſwere, whether the <hi>Theater</hi> reiected him, or he the <hi>Theater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> doth <hi>M. Actor</hi> for his <hi>Muſe</hi> cry out, <hi>Oh Seneca!</hi> whom none ſooner would oppoſe himſelfe againſt Chriſtian pietie. And yet I much doubt of it: For in his Epiſtles he wrote; <hi>It is very dangerous to be preſent at ſuch ſhewes.</hi> And in his firſt Epiſtle of the third Booke, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3558:7"/>the diſſolutneſſe, diſorders, and inconuenience that haue enſued thereby.</p>
               <p>Next doth <hi>M. Actor</hi> deriue his originall of acting <hi>Playes</hi> from the firſt <hi>Olympiad.</hi> When in the preſence of <hi>Hercules</hi> there was perſonated the worthy exploits of his Father <hi>Iupiter:</hi> Which wrought ſuch impreſsion in his minde, that in emulation of his fathers valour, he perform'd his twelue Lobours. Him <hi>Theſeus</hi> followed, and <hi>Achilles Theſcus, &amp;c.</hi> To prooue this falſe, be it manifeſted that there were many <hi>Hercules:</hi> For the Author of <hi>Zenophons aequiuoca,</hi> ſayth; <hi>That the moſt auncient Kinges of Noble families, were ſtill called</hi> Saturnes, <hi>their eldeſt Sonnes</hi> Iupiters, <hi>and their hardieſt Grandchidren</hi> Hercules. <hi>Tully</hi> recounteth ſixe of them:<note place="margin">6. Hercules.</note>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Sonne of the eldeſt <hi>Ioue</hi> &amp; <hi>Liſcitus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. An <hi>Aegiptian</hi> ſonne to <hi>Nilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. One deified amongſt the <hi>Idaeans.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. Sonne to <hi>Aſtery Latona's</hi> Daughter.</item>
                     <item>5. The Indian <hi>Belus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. The third <hi>Iupiters</hi> Sonne by <hi>Alemena. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arro</hi> reckoneth 44.<note place="margin">44. Hercules.</note>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <hi>Siculus</hi> hath but three of them: 1. An <hi>Aegiptian</hi> the worthieſt,<note place="margin">3. Hercules.</note> made Generall of the Armie by <hi>Oſyris:</hi> for ſtrength and vallour, he trauayled moſt part of the World, and erected a Piller in <hi>Lybia:</hi> He liued before the ſecond <hi>Hercules Alcmena's</hi> ſonne aboue 1000. yeares. And this ſecond <hi>Hercules,</hi> emulated him, (not his father <hi>Iupiter</hi>) and therefore was called <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeus.</hi> The third was <hi>Hercules</hi> of <hi>Crete;</hi> a famous Souldier, inſtitutor of the <hi>Olympian</hi> Games. This <hi>Pauſanias</hi> calleth <hi>Idaeus,</hi> which is the third amongſt the ſixe numbred before by <hi>Tully.</hi> And this was that <hi>Hercules</hi> which triumphed as victor on Mount <hi>Olympus:</hi> the other, liued a whole Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration before his time; to whom the ambitious, and fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Greekes</hi> aſcribe the labours of the reſt. And therefore, as he ordained not the <hi>Olympian</hi> Games, ſo neither was he victor of them; for we neuer read of two <hi>Hercules</hi> on the Mount at once: Nor in the firſt <hi>Olympiad</hi> did he behold his Fathers warlike deeds perſonated before him. Wherefore this <hi>M. Actors</hi> Originall of <hi>Playes,</hi> is to be held diſprooued; and that his <hi>Hercules</hi> by probable coniecture, neuer beheld
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3558:8"/>
                  <hi>Play</hi> at all. And ſo as the Propoſition is ouerthrowne, the Aſsumption of others that ſhould imitate him, is diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuld; and conſequently the Concluſion cleane conuinced: and further yet for vnſoundneſſe, to be confounded. For where he ſayth, <hi>It may be imagined had</hi> Achilles <hi>neuer liued,</hi> Alexander <hi>had neuer conquored the World;</hi> Hee is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned euen by <hi>Alexanders</hi> owne wordes: For when he went againſt <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> and that <hi>Iaddus</hi> the High <hi>Prieſt</hi> and the <hi>Leuites</hi> met with him in their Prieſtly roabes, ſhewing him the Viſion of <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Daniel</hi> concerning the <hi>Greekiſh</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie ouer the world: It is recorded that he anſwered. <hi>And this great God by a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſion in my ſleepe encouraged mee to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this weighty enterprize.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alexanders Viſion.</note> So that not the life of <hi>Achilles</hi> acted before him, but the Diuine Viſion prickt him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the performance of his atchiuements. Other things follow, which belonging to the quality of <hi>Playes,</hi> I transferre to handle till the latter part of my Treatiſe, where with other matters together they are to be confuted. But the next proofe of Antiquity for <hi>Stage-Playes</hi> by M <hi>Actor</hi> alleadged, is out of <hi>Ouids</hi> works. That <hi>Playes</hi> were firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Romulus;</hi> which to bee ſuch as <hi>Stage-Playes</hi> are, can neuer be affirmed, but to the contrary. For the <hi>Apologiſt</hi> himſelfe doth alleadge, that the patterne of the firſt Theater in <hi>Rome</hi> was brought from <hi>Athens,</hi> which Act was after the expulſion of their Kings.</p>
               <p>To ſhew then to others (for M <hi>Actor</hi> himſelfe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it) what <hi>Playes</hi> they were,<note place="margin">Romulus his scircenſian Playes.</note> They were <hi>Circenſian Playes,</hi> ſuch as were kept vpon <hi>Olympus</hi> Mount, to proue the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like actiueneſſe of their Youth, in running, leaping, ſword-playing, and the like. And <hi>Circenſes</hi> they were called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the place was encompaſſed with ſwords, of <hi>Circa</hi> and <hi>Enſis,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Seruius.</hi> For the Antiquity hauing not yet or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned fit places wherein to exerciſe their Youth, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed them betwixt a riuer ſide and a ranke of ſwords, that the Idle might ſee danger on both ſides. Afterwards <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinius Priſcus</hi> appoynted a <hi>Ring</hi> for them, that the people
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3558:8"/>might ſtand round, (as wee make a ring for Wraſtlers in <hi>More-fields</hi>) which was called <hi>Circus maximus.</hi> And euery yeere once, ſaith <hi>Liuy,</hi> were theſe Games celebrated, being diuerſly named, as <hi>Magni</hi> &amp; <hi>Romani, &amp; Circenſes.</hi> Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> ground himſelfe vpon his very probable and important argument (as he termes it. <hi>Viz.</hi> That in the time when Theaters moſt flouriſhed at <hi>Rome, Chriſt</hi> and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ſoiourned on the earth: yet neither in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Bookes, Acts or Documents, haue they ſo much as named or touched them, but were content to paſſe them ouer. Manifeſtly falſe; For it is a poynt to bee held, and knowne it is for a truth, that ſome ſinnes there are which neuer were mentioned in holy write in <hi>ſpecie:</hi> and ſhall wee ſay then ſuch are no ſinnes? Nay, ſome ſinnes are in the Scriptures vnſpoken of, which many moſt learned men are of opinion, that they ought not to be publickly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: That the rather being vnknowne, the hardneſſe of mens hearts ſhould not moue them to the committing of ſuch enormities, if knowne they were. This were enough to conuince and refute M. <hi>Actors</hi> important argument, but it ſhall not ſuffice; For it is euen poynted at with the finger both in the olde and in the new Teſtament. In the old, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſetteth downe an euerlaſting morall Law, both for the preſent and future times, <hi>Deut 18.9.</hi> where hee warneth the Iſraelites,<note place="margin">Prooſes of Scipture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſt Playes.</note> that <hi>they ſhould not learne to doe after the abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Gentiles.</hi> And what abhomination was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward more rife among the <hi>Nations,</hi> then <hi>Playes</hi> preſented in honour of their Idols. And in the new Teſtament, S. <hi>Paul 1. Cor chap 8.</hi> commandeth the <hi>Corinthians, that they ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from feaſting in Idols Temples, and from things conſecrate to Idols.</hi> And <hi>Acts 15.20. Write vnto them, that they abſtaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from filthinesse of Idols.</hi> And <hi>Verſ. 29. That they abſtaine themſelues from things offered to Idols.</hi> Now what was offered and conſecrated to the honour of the Idoll Gods or Diuels, more then <hi>Playes?</hi> And what filthineſſe of Idols ſhould they more auoid then <hi>Playes,</hi> which the more obſcene and ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3558:9"/>they were preſented, the better pleaſed they the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels which commanded ſuch ſolemnities to be kept, as ſhall be declared hereafter: wherein maybe eſpied the Diuels drift in inſtituting of them, that through their obſcenity he might corrupt the Gentiles manners.</p>
               <p>Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> obiect, that GOD hath created ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry things for delight: as Iewels, Dainties, and Delicates to be moderately vſed, the Hare to be hunted, the Stagge to be chaſed, &amp;c. All this I denie not. Yet ſhall hee neuer make me beleeue that GOD did euer allow of Iuglers and Sortilegers, often ſpoken againſt by <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor of Ieſters, Vices, and <hi>Players,</hi> which are all of a crue.</p>
               <p>Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> affirme, hee could neuer yet reade any Hiſtory of any Common-wealth which did not thriue and proſper whilſt theſe publicke ſolemnities were had in odoration. Heere doth hee ſeeke to blindfolde the world, and leade vs hoodwinckt in a moſt palpable errour. As though partly <hi>Playes</hi> vpheld the ſlate of a Common-weale, and not rather Vertue cleane oppoſite againſt them. But although the Apologiſt hath produced no example to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme his allegation, yet will I recite worthy memorials to the contrary. <hi>Rome's</hi> Common-wealth which in glory ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed all other, in thoſe times when Theaters moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, then was moſt pitteouſly rent and torne. For a while after the inſtitution of <hi>Stage-playes,</hi> enſued thoſe moſt lamentable ciuill warres that were the ouerthrow of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſtate, as I will now declare</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fall of Romes Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</note>L. <hi>Sylla,</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> two mighty Citizens, through their ambition enuied each other ſo maliciouſly, that their priuate hatred grew into publicke factions. And at laſt their diſcord was ſo great, that they fought a ſet battaile at <hi>Porte Eſquiline.</hi> Where <hi>Marius</hi> being put to the worſt, fled into <hi>Africa. Marius</hi> thus ouercome, <hi>Sylla</hi> going to warre vpon <hi>Mithridates,</hi> left <hi>Cinna,</hi> and <hi>Octauius Conſulles</hi> in the Cittie. But <hi>Cinna</hi> deſirous of innouaſion, ſeuered himſelfe from his fellow, and was chaſed out of the Cittie by him,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3558:9"/>and his faction. Which iniurie <hi>Cinna</hi> endeauouring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, called backe <hi>Marius</hi> out of <hi>Africa.</hi> And he now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth bloudie warres vpon his Country, and entring it with his angry forces, and mighty powers, butchered vp num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in euery corner of the Cittie, charging his Souldiers, that to whom ſo euer he returned not the <hi>ſalute,</hi> they ſhould immediatly diſpatch him: by which meanes an innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble company, noble and ignoble were ſlaughtered. And then in his ſeauenth conſulſhip he died. Soone after came <hi>Sylla</hi> out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and rooted out <hi>Marius</hi> his ſonne, and all the whole faction of them vtterly. And then tooke he vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the perpetuall <hi>Dictator-ſhip:</hi> wherein hee proſcribed many thouſands of the <hi>Romane</hi> Citizens with outragious cruelty, that they all thought <hi>Marius</hi> a meeke Lambe, in reſpect of him, though during his ſuperiority, he tyranized with vnſufferable cruelty and inſolence. So that betweene both, the whole Cittie, Streetes, Market-places, Temples, and Theaters themſelues, were filled with dead carkaſſes. Theſe mens factions, afterwards <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> tooke vp a freſh. <hi>Pompey could endure no equall; and Caeſar no ſuperiour.</hi> So that moſt cruell and deadly warres aroſe betweene them. And at length, <hi>Caeſar</hi> getting the vpper hand, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe perpetuall Dictator, bringeth the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire vnder his owne ſubiection, &amp; reduceth the Common-wealth into a Monarchy. And thus whiles Theaters flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and <hi>Stage playes</hi> were preſented in greateſt pompe, is the moſt flouriſhing eſtate of the <hi>Romane</hi> Common-wealth brought into a Monarchy. To this enſample many more might be added, and yet M. <hi>Actor</hi> could neuer reade of any ſuch Hiſtory. One more I will exhibite and ſo ceaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fall of Caeſars Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie.</note>
                  <hi>Agrippina</hi> the mother of <hi>Nero,</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> his Tutor, both ambitious of gouernment, perſwaded <hi>Nero</hi> in the minority of his age, to take his pleaſures, and leaue vnto them the charge and paine of the publicke affaires of the Empire, thinking that the fury of his youth would ware away with fond delights, and that wiſedome would encreaſe with age,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3558:10"/>in meane time, that they would better gouerne then hee. Of his opinion was <hi>Burrus</hi> a ſingular perſon, and next to <hi>Seneca</hi> in the waighty cauſes of gouernment. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Nero</hi> giues himſelfe to all licentiouſneſſe: now magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent <hi>Theaters</hi> are erected, and <hi>Stage-playes</hi> inſtituted: now the <hi>Poets</hi> pennes are ſet on worke, Tragedians and Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians are buſily occupied: now all theſe flouriſh more then before, or afterwards they euer did. Now <hi>Nero</hi> becommeth a Sword-player, and chaſer of wilde beaſts vpon the <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and thereby commeth to bee butcherous and bloudie minded; afterward a murtherer and a manqueller. Now <hi>Nero</hi> acteth cruell Tragedies and ſcurrilous Comedies in his owne perſon; and thereby learneth to act all diſſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and performe whatſoeuer miſchiefe could be deuiſed: For, <hi>Quo ſemel eſt imbutarecens ſeruabit odorem—Testa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here had ſo ſeaſoned himſelfe in thoſe former euils, and therewith was drawne to ſuch a meruailous corruption, that now he gaddeth about the ſtreetes in the euenings; he and his flattering companions ſets vpon many Innocents he meetes withall, and outragiouſly perpetrateth horrible facts, beaſtlineſſe, and deteſtable murthers. In the meane time, for the ſpace of fiue yeeres, <hi>Seneca</hi> &amp; <hi>Agrippina</hi> gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Empire indifferently. Howbeit, becauſe <hi>Agrippina</hi> tooke vpon her to rule all alone after her owne appetite, theſe two, <hi>Seneca</hi> and <hi>Burrus,</hi> tooke order out of hand, that the Emperour ſhould withdraw the gouernment from her, and aſſume it to himſelfe. But as wiſe as they were, yet were they greatly deceiued, in that they thought <hi>Nero</hi> would become wiſe in age, by paſsing his youth in folly; for it hapned cleane contrary, and hee became a moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and cruell Tyrant: So that at laſt, hauing done innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable miſchiefes againſt one or other, great and ſmall, as his fancieled him, <hi>Seneca</hi> began to doubt leaſt the like might happen to himſelfe. And it came to paſſe, that <hi>Nero's</hi> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, and oppreſsions, ſo wonne him the euill will of all his Subiects, as they one after another reuolted from his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3558:10"/>obeyſance. Whereupon <hi>Burrus, Ruffus, Sulpitius,</hi> and <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius</hi> his greateſt minions, entring into the like feare, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt him; but they were diſcouered and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Yet before they were executed, <hi>Nero</hi> would needes conferre with <hi>Sulpitius</hi> and <hi>Flauius.</hi> And after hee had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of <hi>Sulpitius,</hi> wherefore hee had broken his oath, and conſpir'd againſt him, he asked the like of <hi>Flauius</hi> alſo; who anſwered, <hi>I haue loued, and hated thee</hi> Nero, <hi>aboue any man in the world:<note place="margin">Conspiracie againſt Nero, and why.</note> Loued thee, as long as there was any hope thou wouldeſt become a good Prince: but when I ſaw thee become a Manqueller, a Murtherer, a Tragedian, a Player of Enterludes, a Fencer, and a Towne-burner, I could not but hate thee extreamely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is euidently to be ſeene the effects of theſe <hi>Theaters,</hi> how it made <hi>Nero</hi> to be hated of his deareſt friends. Whoſe anſweres though they aſtonied him to heare, yet in ſteed of amendment, he addicted himſelfe to farre worſe enormities then before. So that behold <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>index</hi> his Lieutenant gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in <hi>Gaul,</hi> reuolted from him: Wherewith though the loſſe were not ſmall, yet was not <hi>Nero</hi> much troubled. But when hee vnderſtood that his olde Captaine <hi>Galba</hi> Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of <hi>Spaine,</hi> was reuolted, then too late hee feared his owne ruine. And now began the Empire ſodainly to bee rent in ſunder, for almoſt euery Gouernour ceaſed their Prouinces into their owne hands. Then doth <hi>Galba</hi> haſten vnto <hi>Rome</hi> to diſpatch the Tyrant: who in the end, being abandoned of euery one, euen thoſe of his owne guard, fled and hid himſelfe within a little Lodge in the Fields; where fearing to be taken aliue, hee kild himſelfe. And after this ſort was the blood of the <hi>Caeſars</hi> extinguiſhed, and no more Emperours by lawfull ſucceſsion. For the pretorian cohorts became ſo diſſolute in <hi>Nero's</hi> raigne, that both they and the other Souldiers tooke vpon them to create Emperours at their pleaſure: Whereby the Empire oftentimes was miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably diſmembred by ſundry Tyrants at once by them are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. And thus to conclude, whiles <hi>Playes</hi> were had in greateſt honour, by the corruption of manners that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3558:11"/>from them, was the <hi>Romane</hi> Common-wealth changed into a Monarchie, and the Monarchie afterwards into Tyrannicall gouernement.</p>
               <p>Next, doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> with great contumely ſcandalize the good Emperour <hi>Marcus Aurilius,</hi> calling him <hi>Cynick,</hi> and vnfit for gouernment. In meane while, condemning the vſe of <hi>Comedies,</hi> which ſo cynically (as him ſelfe would haue it) barke at al follies: And likewiſe obnubilating his worthineſſe, for whoſe loue, who baniſhed <hi>Players,</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple made them all Statues in his memoriall; which they vouchſafed for no other Emperour, no not for <hi>Auguſtus</hi> him ſelfe, whom the <hi>Apologiſt</hi> affirmes to be greateſt patron of <hi>Poets</hi> and <hi>Players</hi> in his time. Nor did that good Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour interdict the vſe of Theaters, becauſe the wanton Dames of <hi>Rome</hi> made a <hi>Play</hi> of him; but becauſe of the great folly they wrought, &amp; the corruption of goodneſſe which they brought into <hi>Rome,</hi> as ſhall further hereaſter appeare in a Letter of his, written to <hi>Lambertus</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſpont,</hi> when he ſent him three Shippes of <hi>Ieſters</hi> and <hi>Players,</hi> wiſhing to haue but one Barke of <hi>Wiſe</hi> men in returne of his aduenture. Nor did hee baniſh Sword-players for other cauſe, then the peſtilence of minde wherewith the people by bloody ſpectacls might be infected, to the perpetrating of any butcherous attempt: not that himſelfe was a cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard; for he twice triumphed: once when hee ouercame the <hi>Parthians;</hi> and once when h conquered the <hi>Argonauts,</hi> and died in conquering the Realme of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next, doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> looke backe from <hi>Italy</hi> into <hi>Greece,</hi> declaring that the Princes and Sages thereof, being thoſe which were the firſt vnderſtanders, trained vp their youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Nobilitie to be <hi>Actors,</hi> debarring the <hi>Mechanicks</hi> ſuch imployment. In which, is diuers things to be noted, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed: Firſt, that not all <hi>Greece</hi> is to be vnderſtood, for <hi>Sparta</hi> is to be exempted as reiecting ſuch abuſes. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how doth he derogate from the glory of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> when heriportes that the <hi>Grecians</hi> were the firſt Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanders,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3558:11"/>whereas it is euident by all Hiſtory,<note place="margin">the Grecians not the firſt wiſe men.</note> the <hi>Grecians</hi> receiued their knowledg from the <hi>Aegiptians,</hi> and <hi>Chaldocans,</hi> and they from the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> But if erecting of <hi>Playes</hi> were ſuch an act, that it were worthy the firſt vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to performe, how then chanced it the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> did it not? among whom we neuer read <hi>Stage-playes</hi> to be ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, and therefore neuer ſpoken of, nor taxed <hi>in ſpecie</hi> by the Prophets in their bookes. Thirdly it may bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded why the <hi>Grecians</hi> prohibited the baſer ſort from ſuch imployment. Surely I know not, except their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks were, and they alſo deſired they ſhould be, of honeſter life and behauiour then their nobility. According to that ſpeech of <hi>Aemilius probus</hi> treating of the <hi>Greekiſh</hi> faſhions, <hi>In thoſe Countries</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>its no diſgrace for any man</hi> (heere M. Actor is found tripping for debarring me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks) <hi>to come vpon the Stage, to ſet himſelfe as aſpectacle to the people:</hi> which we hold for partly infamous, and partly baſe and vnworthy of an honeſt man.</p>
               <p>Next doth M. Actor ſhew why the <hi>Grecians</hi> admitted <hi>Playes.</hi> Which becauſe it toucheth the vſe of <hi>Playes</hi> I will leaue, perticulerly to handle it in my Third treatiſe.</p>
               <p>Next followes that through Poets and Actors the <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> excelled in Ciuilitie and gouernment, ſo that other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions borrowed their lawes of them. The <hi>Romans</hi> indeed ſent to take a patterne of the <hi>Athenian</hi> lawes, and withall a while after erected a Theater, after the patterne of the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian:</hi> and a while after this againe; the lawes of <hi>Athens</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them not to Ciuilitie ſo much, as by the induction of <hi>Playes</hi> they fell into diſſoluteneſſe. Through which all things ranne into diſorder, and Ciuilitie laid aſide, inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie ſprang vp inſteed thereof. For then preſently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the wars they had againſt their own ſlaues, &amp; ſword-players, Then enſued, as I ſaid before, the Factions of <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> and after that betweene <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> the end whereof was the vtter ſubuerſion of their common wealth. And now, if through <hi>Stage-playes</hi> the <hi>Grecians</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:3558:12"/>learned Ciuilitie, &amp; good gouernment, how could it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be, but that the <hi>Romanes</hi> hauing both their lawes and theaters, ſhould alſo excell in Ciuilitie, (for from the ſame cauſes proceede the ſame efiects.) and not that a while after through the <hi>Grecian</hi> inſtitutions, they ſhould learne inſteed of good manners, corruption; inſteed of concord, faction; and all kind of diſorder,<note place="margin">Playes profited not the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to ciuilitie.</note> inſteed of reformation. Therefore as <hi>Playes</hi> did not benefit the <hi>Romanes,</hi> ſo neither could they profit the <hi>Grecians.</hi> Whereby wee may perceaue how M. <hi>Actor</hi> to blind his readers mind, would faine impoſe more vpon the worth of theaters, then poſſibly could be inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And yet doth he confeſſe, that thoſe times of the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> was but the childhood and infancy of the world, very fitly; For indeed it was but their fooliſh thought, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh opinion, that <hi>Playes</hi> was the readieſt way to plant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in the ignorant, whereas in the riper, and now old age of the world, moſt men haue receiued a true intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, to the contrary, except ſuch onely as remaine children ſtill.</p>
               <p>Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> would faine ſeeme to ſhorten the extent of the Text and expreſſe commandement of God in <hi>Deute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronomic.</hi> 22.5. <hi>The woman ſhall not weare that which appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the man; neither ſhall a man put on womans raiment.</hi> Where although the Law is indifferently to be vnderſtood of both Sexes, yet more ſtrictly concerning the man, that he ſhould not ſo much as put on womans raiment. A very impudent and common abuſe in playes it is, though M. <hi>Actor</hi> would willingly dawbe ouer the meaning of the Scripture, as though that conſiſted in the like figuratiue ſence, as the words of ſacramentall conſecration elſewhere doe. Whereas there is as much difference betweene that trope and theſe plaine words, as betweene a <hi>Rope</hi> and a <hi>Player.</hi> And although Playes are not immediately meant in the Text, becauſe in that time there was none in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> nay nor during the whole time, wherein the Church of GOD was planted among the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> was ſuch vanities
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3558:12"/>knowne among them: yet doth it immediately point at this abuſe of wearing womens apparell, (vſed in Playes,) flatly forbidding it.</p>
               <p>Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> affirmes, that the Vniuerſities ſometime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute <hi>Stage-playes:</hi> more is the pittie, that the moſt famous lights of learning in the world ſhould bee branded with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie, through the meanes of ſome phantaſticals which are in them. Wherefore admit they doe:<note place="margin">Who make and act plaies in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſities.</note> who them moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly doe compoſe their Playes? Idle braines, that affect not their better ſtudies. Who are the Actors? Gentle-bloods, and luſty ſwaſh-bucklers, ſuch as prefer an ounce of vaine-glorie, oſtentation, and ſtrutting on the Stage, before a pound of learning; and are ſent to the Vniuerſities, not ſo much to obtaine knowledge, as to keepe them from the common ryot of Gentlemen in theſe daies: like little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whom their parents ſent to ſchoole, the rather to keep them from vnder horſes feet in the ſtreets, which carefull mothers doe ſo greatly feare. And who are the ſpectators? but ſuch like as both Poets and Actors are, euen ſuch as reckon no more of their ſtudies, then <hi>ſpend-all</hi> Gentlemen of their caſt ſutes.</p>
               <p>But what followes in the <hi>Apology?</hi> Theſe <hi>Playes</hi> embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the <hi>Iunior</hi> ſchollers againſt they come to read the pub-like Lecture of <hi>Dialect, Ethick, Mathematick, Phiſick</hi> and <hi>Metaphiſick.</hi> And why not among theſe the Diuinitie Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture? becauſe certainely no ſuch prophane, and light hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded perſons may bee admitted to it, and becauſe according to the ſaying of Pope <hi>Panl</hi> 2. and <hi>Adrian</hi> 6. they are to bee held as enemies to true Religion.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Plaies</hi> as ſaith the <hi>Apologyſt</hi> makes a bold <hi>Sophiſter,</hi> that is plainely, a too cunning, or falſe reaſoner, to knit pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous and intertangled ſyllogiſmes, obſcure Sorites, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nig maticall Crocodilites, and forke-horned <hi>Dilemma's</hi> to enſnare and obnubilate the truth: as now M. <hi>Actor</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe faine would doe.</p>
               <p>Next follows <hi>Playes</hi> eſpeciall vſe for <hi>Rhetorick. Rhetorica
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3558:13"/>eſt ars bone dicendi. Rhetorick</hi> is an Art <hi>of ſpeaking well.</hi> And <hi>Playes</hi> in th' <hi>Apologie</hi> inſtruct to ſpeake well.<note place="margin">Playes vſe for Rhetorick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuted.</note> Surely M. <hi>Actor</hi> would be eſteemed for a <hi>Rhetorician,</hi> and haue <hi>Plaies</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one of the ſeuen liberall <hi>Arts:</hi> but his drift is not dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen home enough. For <hi>vltra poſſe, non eſt eſſe.</hi> Who euer of the ancient <hi>Orators, Greekes,</hi> or <hi>Latins,</hi> learned to ſpeake well from a <hi>Play?</hi> Did <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> learne his Science from a Stage? Did <hi>Cicero</hi> learne his <hi>Oratory</hi> from a Theater? Why doe not our Diuine <hi>Orators</hi> ſchoole themſelues by <hi>Playes,</hi> thereby to learne <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> ſo neceſſary in their Sennons? But they know well, that <hi>Playes</hi> are a fictiue Art, and not a liberall Science: they know well that <hi>Rhetorick</hi> graceth <hi>Playes</hi> by the inſtruction it giues, for breathing ſpaces, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, and good deliuery of words, and not that poeſie and <hi>Playes</hi> euer gaue that facultie to <hi>Rhetorick.</hi> For the <hi>firſt arts giue light vnto the arts ſucceeding.</hi> And <hi>Rhetorick</hi> was long found out before <hi>posſie.</hi> For no ſooner had God giuen to men language in the beginning, but that preſently expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience taught them, how aptly to apply their words, how to perſwade, and diſwade, how to exhort, diſcourage, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, praiſe or diſpraiſe, defend, confute, extenuate and ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauate any matter, and conſequently how to riſe and fall with the voice, to ſtop, to breath, diſtinguiſh, interrogate, and to obſerue all other elegancie of ſpeech.</p>
               <p>Next, and laſt of all doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> euen as in the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſo in the later ending of his firſt Booke, callumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate thoſe worthy and Reuerend Preachers, that in their godly Sermons, out of conſcience are ſtudious to ſuppreſſe theſe obſcaene and filthy Stage-playes. And I, as in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, muſt reprehend and reproue him therefore. That out of the cuſtome of malicious <hi>Comedian</hi> detrectation on the Stage, and not of conſcience and reaſon hee doth ſo reuile them.</p>
               <p>Now haue I runne ouer the chiefe points and arguments, of the firſt Treatiſe of M. <hi>Actors Apologie,</hi> confuting ſome things, and diſprouing other: wherein this one thing yet is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3558:13"/>to bee noted; That the very ſubiect of <hi>Actors</hi> Antiquity, both for their Originall and firſt Induction into <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Antiquitas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n veritate eſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquus error.</note> is yet more narrowly to be inueſtigated. For neither <hi>Hercules</hi> at the firſt <hi>Olympiad</hi> beheld his Father <hi>Iupiters</hi> Acts perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before him, for that, that <hi>Hercules,</hi> which ordained the <hi>Olympian games,</hi> was not <hi>Iupiters</hi> Sonne, and two <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> we neuer read to haue beene preſent at theſe games at once: neither did <hi>Romulus</hi> firſt inſtitute Stage-plaies at <hi>Rome,</hi> but as I ſaid before, <hi>Circenſian games,</hi> euen ſuch as were vſed in the <hi>Olympiads,</hi> to exerciſe their youth withall: as running, riding, leaping, tourncying, ſword-playing, courſing with Chariots, and the like. Wherefore to doe M. <hi>Actor</hi> an ouerthwart kindneſſe, I will out of ſundry Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors declare both their Originall, and when, and by what meanes, and by whoſe, they firſt came into <hi>Rome.</hi> After which, with ſome few notes and obſeruations, I will finiſh this firſt part of my Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Originall of Playes.</note>The old Husbandmen of <hi>Greece,</hi> vſing euery yeare to ſacrifice to <hi>Bacchus</hi> for their fruits: Firſt vſed in ſtead of Prayers, to ſing ſomething at putting the fire to the Altars. And then to pleaſe his Deity the better, they ſung ouer all his victories, warres, conqueſts, and captiuation of Kings. For reward of which their paines, a Goat was firſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or the skinne of a Goat full of Wine. But becauſe the Kings that <hi>Bacchus</hi> had conquered; affoorded not matter enough for their yearely ſongs, they fell in hand with the calamities of other Kings, and ſung much of them. And this ſong was called a <hi>Tragedy:</hi> either of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Goate, which they offered to <hi>Bacchus</hi> as an enemy to the Vines, or which was the reward of the ſingers; or of the <hi>Wine leeſe</hi> with which they beſmeared their faces, (before that <hi>Aeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilus</hi> deuiſed vizors for them) called in <hi>Greek</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Some will haue the <hi>Comedie</hi> to haue had the Originall from theſe Sacrifices alſo. Others from the ſolemnities of <hi>Apollo No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius,</hi> the Guardian of Shepheards and Villages. Some ſay, that both theſe Sacrifices were celebrated at once. Follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3558:14"/>which, the moſt common opinion is thus. When the <hi>Athenians</hi> liued as yet in diſperſed Cotages (<hi>Theſeus</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not yet reduced them to Cittie) the Husbandmen v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed after their Sacrifices, to breake ieſts vpon ſuch as were preſent, and ſuch as trauailed by chance that way: and by theſe mirthfull ſcoffes delighted all the companie. Now, after that the Citty was builded, the Husbandmen at the time appointed for the ſolemnities, came into the Towne in Carts, and ieſted one while at their Fellowes, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while at the Cittizens, cheefely ſuch as had offended them. And this was called a <hi>Comedie:</hi> either of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, becauſe they liued in ſuch, or of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a way, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be ſaucy, or to reuell, becauſe they were profuſe, and ſpared no man in the way with their petulant quips. And this is rather the true deriuation; for as <hi>Lod. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iues</hi> ſaith, the <hi>Athenians</hi> as then did not call their Villages <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This cuſtome pleaſed the Cittizens, and made them animate theſe of the prompter wit, to write more exactly in this kind of verſe. Now the Cittie Poets at firſt taxed the vices of the Cittizens with bitternes, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards when they began to follow their owne affects, and their friends, excerciſing their grudges with ſharpnes, and vſing their pens for their weapons, they would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time traduce Princes that neuer had deſerued any ſuch matter, and euen name them. Which tricke when <hi>Eupolis</hi> had plaied with <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> in his <hi>Comedie</hi> called <hi>Baptis,</hi> he cauſed him to bee taken and throwne into the Sea, ſaying theſe words: <hi>Thou haſt often drowned mee vpon the Stage,</hi> Eupolis, <hi>I will once drowne thee in the Sea.</hi> By which exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the reſt of the Poets were ſo terrified, that <hi>Alcibiades</hi> got a law paſt, that none ſhould dare to name any man vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stage. So that kind of <hi>Comedie</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, the old <hi>Comedie</hi> was aboliſhed. Then came in the ſecond kind; wherein many were girded at priuy ſuppreſſing of Names vnder colours. And this the Nobilitie fell in diſlike withall, leaſt their facts ſhould be glanced at vnder-hand.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3558:14"/>So that was taken quite away, and a new kind inuented; which treated of meaner perſons vnder change of names, wherein was more moderation in their taxation. Theſe kinds were all in <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for the time of Stage-playes firſt entrance into <hi>Rome,</hi> by what meanes, and by whom they were firſt induced, it followeth thus. In the 400 yeare, or thereabout, of <hi>Romes</hi> foundation, there was ſuch a ſore plague in the Cittie, that they determined not to number the thouſands which were dead, but the few that remained yet aliue. And then their Gods (which the holy Scriptures ſheweth to be Deuils) for the asswaging of the Peſtilence,<note place="margin">Playes firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted in Rome by the commaund of Deuils.</note> that ſeiſed on their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and for the augmentation of their Religion; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded an inſtitution of Stage-playes preſently to bee effected in their Honors, and annexed to the celebration of their Sacrifices. And yet that bodily Peſtilence did not ceaſe, becauſe that delicate vanity of Stage-playes entred into the cares of the people, which were then wholy giuen to warres, and accuſtomed onely to the <hi>Circenſian games.</hi> For <hi>Liuce</hi> in his ſeauenth Booke, ſaith: <hi>This firſt inſtitution of Playes for augmentation of Religion, did neither augment Religion in their minds, nor diminiſh the Peſtilence in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</hi> But the wily Deuils knowing by naturall reaſon, that the plague ſhould once haue an end, and beeing not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied that they had already infected <hi>Greece,</hi> but they would alſo corrupt <hi>Rome,</hi> and by her, afterwards all the world: by this meanes tooke occaſion to thruſt a farre worſe plague, not into their bodies, but into their manners, ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in corrupting of which lyeth all their ioy. And ſurely the Deuill would neuer haue inſtituted Playes, but that he knew they were, and would bee beneficiall to his Kingdome.</p>
               <p>One example or authority more I will produce to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this, that the Celebration of Playes was by comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to pacifie their Gods. <hi>Tully</hi> (in <hi>Verrem, Acti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 6.</hi>) being made <hi>Aedile,</hi> cryes out in the cares of the Cittie; <hi>I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3558:15"/>must needs preſent the moſt ſacred Playes and Ceremoniall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities vnto</hi> Ceres, Liber, <hi>and</hi> Proſerpina: <hi>then I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile Mother</hi> Flora <hi>vnto the Citty and people of Rome, with the celebration of her enterludes.</hi> By this its euident, that theſe vanities were not firſt brought vp in <hi>Rome</hi> by the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of men, but by the direct commandement of Idol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuils And then aroſe the <hi>Comedie</hi> wherein they caſt forth fluttiſh Phraſes, and bitter Quips. And this they did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably in verſes, called <hi>Feſcenini,</hi> of ſuch a Cittie in <hi>Hetruria,</hi> from whence they had their firſt Players, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them <hi>Hiſtriones</hi> in the language of that Country. In their taxations they neuer durſt name any; for that was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden in their Law of the twelue Tables. But theſe <hi>Feſcenine vſes</hi> wore out of the Playes by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: and being it was not allowable to traduce any man by name vpon the State, there ſprang vp diuers ſorts of theſe playing Fables in <hi>Italy,</hi> euen as there did in <hi>Greece;</hi> as the New <hi>Comedie</hi> and the <hi>Satyr:</hi> not that which taxeth Vices, and is bound to that one kinde of Verſe vſed by <hi>Horace, Perſius,</hi> and <hi>Iuuenal,</hi> but that wherein the <hi>Satyrs</hi> were brought in, in a ſluttiſh and opprobrious manner; as in <hi>hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Coats, heauy paced, and altogether vnbandſome and ſlouenly.</hi> The firſt true Comedy in Lattine Verſe (as M. <hi>Actor</hi> alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth) was written by <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius Andronicus, Solinater's</hi> freed Seruant, after Rome was buildediuſt 540. yeares, the firſt <hi>Carthagenian</hi> warre being ended ſome few yeares before, as <hi>Atticus</hi> doth account the time.</p>
               <p>But to conclude this Diſcourſe, there were foure cheefe ſorts of Stage-Playes among the Romaines. <hi>Comedies, Tragedies, Satyrs,</hi> and <hi>Mimick's,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> or plaine-feete, wearing neither ſhooes nor buskins, but comming bare-foote vpon the Stage. The <hi>Satyrs</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and the <hi>Mimicks,</hi> are both included vnder the <hi>Comedie.</hi> The <hi>Tragedie</hi> diſcourſeth of lamentable fortunes, extream affects, horrible villanies, rapines, murthers, ſpoils, tyrannies, and the like. The <hi>Comedie</hi> treats of Fables, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſties,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3558:15"/>all kinde of knaueries and trickes of wanton Loue, (the impious ſubiects of theſe playes would make one hate them) beeing brought into it by <hi>Menander,</hi> to pleaſe the <hi>Macedonians</hi> that ſtood affected in ſuch paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Satyr</hi> containeth the looſer <hi>Faunes</hi> and <hi>Siluanes,</hi> whoſe Ruſticall Ieſts delight much. But as they were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanly and ſlouenly, ſoe were their ſpeeches very foule and diſhoneſt to heare. The Mimicks forbare no beaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but vſed extreame licentiouſneſſe; And yet were theſe more tollerable then other thinges acted in the ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> which after for their incredible villany and filthineſſe, were expelled out of Italy by a decree of the Senate. The <hi>Saturnalia</hi> and <hi>Floralia</hi> were two other kind of Playes celebrated by common Strumpets, and the moſt raskally ſort of all men. The Actors of the <hi>Floralia</hi> though they reuerenced not their owne Gods, yet when <hi>Cato</hi> came, they would not for ſhame act any thing in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
               <p>I feare me I haue beene too tedious; yet haue I continued my diſcourſe, that I might declare concerning Playes and their originall ſomewhat to the full. Out of which prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent diſcourſe ſome thinges are yet to bee noted, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched at againe.</p>
               <p>Firſt concerning their Originall, that they were firſt inſtituted amongſt the fabulous Heathen Greekes (the peruerters of all Diuine knowledge) in honour of their Diuell-Gods. And that the <hi>Comedies</hi> tooke their matter and ſubiect from enuious ieſting and ſcoffing (practiſed now in our enterludes) ſtrictly forbidden by the Apoſtle. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.4. and 4.31.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that their firſt induction into <hi>Rome</hi> was by the commandement of theſe Diuell-Gods. For which cauſe it ſelfe, as thinges the Diuell moſt delighted in, all profeſſing the name of Chriſtians ſhould deteſt.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3558:16"/>
               <p>Laſtly that the Actors and Poets were driuen to poſt from one kind of Play to another, becauſe they were euer in diſlike and becauſe their licentiouſneſſe euer grew to bee ſuch and ſo great, (as theirs among vs now is) that it was not tollerable.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nec parcit cuiquam veſtrae petulantia linguae,</l>
                  <l>Quid mirum ſi vos eadem quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, fulmina tangunt?</l>
               </q>
               <trailer>The end of the Firſt Book.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <head>A Refutation of the Apology for Actors, and of their ancient and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne indignity.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE SECOND BOOKE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow I haue ended my firſt Treatiſe, it followes that I proceed in confutation of M. <hi>Actors</hi> ſecond Booke, <hi>Of Actors antient Dignity.</hi> Wherein, after I haue refuted ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, I will declare how the Antiquity eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them, and what baſe accompt for the moſt part they made of them. To be breefe therefore, the firſt thing that M. <hi>Actor</hi> offereth to his Reader is an <hi>Apothegme</hi> of <hi>Cicero</hi> &amp; <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Wherein is euident how vnneceſſary in a common weallth <hi>Caeſar</hi> at firſt eſteemed Players for to bee, in that therevppon hee pretended a Cauill againſt them. But ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that <hi>Cicero's</hi> opinion of Playes, <hi>viz. That many heads
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3558:16"/>were buſied with them which otherwiſe would bee inquiſitiue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his greatnes,</hi> tooke place in <hi>Caeſars</hi> head, ſo that (as M. <hi>Actor</hi> would pretend) hee gaue many priuiledges to men of that quality. But both <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> were deceiued in their Councells, for it polited <hi>Caeſar</hi> not one lot. For all the while Playes then floriſhed, <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſsius</hi> with 60. Senators more, were buſied in Conſpiracy againſt him, and at laſt trecherouſly kild him with daggers in <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peys</hi> Court. Belike they among others were not buſied with the Playes: nay; bee it more likely that from Playes (which are ſtuffed full of ſuch matters) they learned the cleanely conueyance of their trechery, and how, in what ſort, with what ſecrecy, and by what meanes to effect their treaſon.</p>
               <p>Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> ſhew ſundry examples of ſtately and ſumptuous theaters, erected for Stagerits, and of one in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall made by <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> wherein was figured the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall motion of the coeleſtiall Spheares. But in his deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hee hath acted the Play-poet ſo exceeding well, or rather declared ſuch hyperbolicall impoſſibilities,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Actor</hi> his forgery.</note> that any hauing euer but taſted of the Mathematick arts, will ſmell out his forgery, whereby hee ſeekes to dignifie his profeſſion. But I muſt needs confeſſe too ſumptuous theaters were built by the great Princes of the world. But who were they more then mecre Heathen men and very Athieſts, moſt of them vnthrifts and profuſe ſpenders? of whom, ſome for their owne vaine-glory and oſtentation erected Theaters: others in honour of their Diuell-Gods which commanded it, and others to ſhew their magnificence, and what they were out of ſuperfluity able to performe. As <hi>Traian</hi> the Emperour built a bridge ouer the riuer <hi>Danubius,</hi> euen where it was narroweſt, by reaſon whereof it became more difficult: For there the ſpatious ſtreame being curbd in, made the torrent more ſwift then otherwhere. Which againe <hi>Adrian</hi> his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor ruinated, becauſe it was a worke of coſt ſo vainely ſpent. And are not theſe Princes, with their reaſons, for what end they built Theaters, worthy examples for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3558:17"/>Potentates to imitate? If they are, ſurely none but ſuch as <hi>Machianel</hi> will contend to proue it.</p>
               <p>After this againe doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> recount ſundry Theaters in diuers Prouinces and Emporiall Citties, ſome ruinated (as thinges repudiated) ſome built by Heathen Ethnicks, ſome by Popiſh Catholicks, ſome for the hardneſſe of peoples hearts, tollerated in the reformed Churches, and amongſt others, one of eſpeciall note by Popiſh King <hi>Francis. Anno</hi> 1539. wherein for 30. dayes together were repreſented the Acts of the Apoſtles. Concerning this let all true Chriſtians giue their cenſure, whether this act of King <hi>Francis</hi> was not moſt impious and ſacrilegious, that he ſhould prophane the holy Scripture on a ſtage. Yet doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> approue him for it: for hee traduceth him as a great dignifier of Stagerits. If this be true then let not M. <hi>Actor</hi> bee adiudged for a true Chriſtian, vntill hee ſing a <hi>Palinode,</hi> in recantation of his Apology.</p>
               <p>Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> ſpend many words in repetition of a whole crew of Poets and Actors, ancient and moderne, and amongſt them hee extolls one of eſpeciall note and fame in Rome, by name <hi>Roſcius.</hi> Of him thus ſaith D. <hi>Anthony de Gueuara</hi> in his <hi>Dial of Princes.</hi> We find (ſaith hee) ſome fragments of an Oration which <hi>Cicero</hi> made in the Senate, greatly reprouing the Senators, and all the people becauſe they ſo willingly gaue eare to this ieſter which raiſed ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among the commons, his name was <hi>Roſcio;</hi> who was ſo highly eſteemed in <hi>Rome,</hi> that the <hi>Romanes</hi> more willingly heard his ieſts, then that which <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpake in good earneſt. This Ieſter <hi>Roſcio</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> ſtriued which of them both were the better. <hi>Roſcio</hi> for preſenting a thing with diuers ieſts, or <hi>Cicero</hi> for pronouncing waighty matters in earneſt. When I read (ſaith hee) in <hi>Iulius Capitolinus</hi> that which I haue ſpoken, I confeſſe that I could not refraine my ſelfe from laughter, to ſee that <hi>Roſcio</hi> being Prince of folly, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to contend with <hi>Cicero,</hi> which was father of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:3558:17"/>
               <p>Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> ſhewes what kind of men he would Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhould bee: ſuch, that although they cannot ſpeak wel, yet know how, or ſuch that haue volubility (their tongue to run afore their wit) and can ſpeake well, though they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not what. See ſee his abſurdity heerein. He would in his firſt Booke faine make acting an Art <hi>Rhetoricall,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing to ſpeake well, and yet the tutors in it to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for their functions. All Arts conſiſt of two partes: <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> and <hi>practiſe.</hi> Now for the firſt ſort ſuch as cannot ſpeak well cannot teach the part practick of the Art: and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſort, ſuch as vnderſtand not what they ſpeake, cannot teach the part methodicall. And ſo conſequently no perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Players is to bee attained in <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> or the art of ſpeaking well, if to bee an Art it were admitted. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which read againe <hi>Page</hi> 17.18.</p>
               <p>Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> could wiſh (but he will not) that ſuch as are condemned for their licentiouſneſſe, were excluded their ſociety. And wiſh long enough hee may without redreſſe, himſelfe among others neuer ſeeking for it. For exempt their licentiouſneſſe only out of Playes, too too ſmall alas will bee their gettings to maintaine their idle life; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thing which moſt pleaſeth the multitude, who chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly run flocking to the Play-houſe, that they might make mirth of ſuch folly and laugh at it, and that they might tell it to others when they come home, to make more fooles laugh for company. And therefore in vaine afterwards doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> intreat for excuſe; not to miſdeeme all for the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds of ſome; being it is the generall carriage of them all. It is a rule in Diuinity to know a mans conditions and what hee is, by the company hee doth vſually keepe. Now if the beſt of them were not licentious, why do they liue, and Ioue, accompany, and play together with them which are. Were it not madneſſe for a man to be his companion which is his daily reproch? But Players all of them are licencious: for, the prouerb is, <hi>Birds of a feather flye together.</hi> And therefore if they were not they would neuer aſſociate them which are,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3558:18"/>whon the <hi>Syntereſis</hi> of their owne conſcience, and the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience of all men willeth to auoyd.</p>
               <p>Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> recite a memorable example of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar,</hi> that ſlew his own ſeruant whiles he acted <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les furens</hi> on the Stage. Which example indeed greatly doth make againſt their Playes. For it's not vnlikely but a Player might doe the like now,<note place="margin">Facyfull ſights likely to happen et Playes.</note> as often they haue done. And then what a lamentable proiect would there be for the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators to behold: As many times it happens when their ſuppoſed nocent perſons are falſely hanged, and diuers of them ready to be ſtrangld, or altogether. As for the other Emperours which were Actors by th' <hi>apologiſt</hi> recorded: as <hi>Caligula, Nero, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itellius, Domitianus,</hi> and <hi>Commodus,</hi> all Hiſtory ſhewes they were the moſt bloody, mercileſſe, and cruell Villaines breath'd; <hi>Fit to make Actors, though fit for nothing elſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> proſecute his matter with example from the Papiſts, though hee would excuſe himſelfe for it with <hi>haec breter me</hi> at the end thereof. But how impious it is to prophane holy Scripture as they doe, all true Chriſtians can determine, as I haue ſaid before. And for ſuch prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Players many times haue receiued their due deſerts: as may appeare by the moſt fearfull accident that happened to the Ieſuites of late yeeres at <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> when they would needs Act a <hi>Play</hi> of Chriſts comming to Iudgement at the laſt day. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his Booke <hi>De preapar. Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelica,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b.<hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> cap.<hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> ſets downe an Hiſtory of a Poet that ſodainly loſt his Naturall ſight, for hauing lewdly applied a peece of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to a Fable.</p>
               <p>Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> ſhew out of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil,</hi> that <hi>Theaters</hi> were erected immediatly after the Ruine of <hi>Troy.</hi> But ſurely M. <hi>Actor</hi> is not acquainted with <hi>Virgil</hi> though he be a <hi>Poet.</hi> If he were, then verily he is not ignorant, how <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil</hi> doth apply auncient Monuments and memorials to his time. As when hee faineth a prophecie, that from <hi>Iulus</hi> ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed another of like name, which ſhould gouerne the ſtate of <hi>Rome,</hi> meaning <hi>Iulius Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3558:18"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Naſcetur pulcra Troianus origine Caeſar,</l>
                  <l>Imperium Oceano, famam qui terminent aſtris,<note place="margin">Virg. Aened <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Iulius, a magno demiſſum nomen Iulo,</l>
               </q>
               <p>Likewiſe elſewhere doth <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil</hi> faine <hi>Dido</hi> to prophecie of the <hi>Romane</hi> and <hi>Carthaginean</hi> continuall hatred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in long time after there chanced ſuch continuall warres betweene them.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Tum vos ô Tyrijſtirpem,</l>
                  <l>Exercete odijs, cinerique, haec mittue nostro<note place="margin">Aeneid. l. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Munera: nullus amor populis nec foedera ſunto.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> ſaith, That he hath diſcourſt of <hi>Theaters</hi> euen till the Raigne of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> and how they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their glory (he forgets that <hi>Tyberius</hi> (witneſſe <hi>Corn: Tacitus annalum lib.</hi> 4.) droue them out of <hi>Italy</hi>) till the time of <hi>Marc. Aurelius,</hi> (who baniſhed them into <hi>Helleſpont:</hi>) And from him euen to theſe times. Ho there, ſtay a little good <hi>Sir.</hi> To skip aboue a thouſand yeeres is nothing with M. <hi>Actor.</hi> For from the time of <hi>Constantine</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> who ſuppreſſed <hi>Playes</hi> as did <hi>Aurelius,</hi> till the time of <hi>Richard</hi> 2. of <hi>England, Anno</hi> 1390. and <hi>Edward</hi> 4. <hi>Anno</hi> 1490. and <hi>Francis</hi> the French King <hi>Anno</hi> 1539, hee hath nothing to ſay for himſelfe. But he muſt now needs confeſſe that when Chriſtianitie began publikely to flouriſh,<note place="margin">As Chriſtians encreiſed ſo P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> were more and mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aboliſhed.</note> then Paganiſme dayly more and more was aboliſhed, and at the laſt vtterly extinct in Chriſtendome: till of late yeeres firſt Papiſticall Fryers and Ieſuits raiſed it vp a-freſh.</p>
               <p>Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> alledge authoritie from <hi>Cicero,</hi> to proue that <hi>Playes</hi> were both in <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Lacedemon.</hi> In <hi>Athens</hi> indeed they were, but neuer in <hi>Lacedemonia.</hi> Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily there might bee <hi>Theaters,</hi> or places of proſpect to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their actiue youth ſhew their martiall feates, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like proweſſe, at certaine times of the yeere, as the Romans
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3558:19"/>in their <hi>Circenſian Playes,</hi> and <hi>ludis ſecularibus,</hi> ſecular games. But it was neuer read that <hi>Hyſtriones, Actors, Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> or <hi>Comedians</hi> were in <hi>Lacedemon.</hi> For <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>Apothegmes</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> neuer permitted any ſuch in their common-wealth. And that when an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of <hi>Rhodes</hi> demanded a <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> what was the occaſion of their lawes againſt ſuch, ſince that the Ieſters and Players ſhewed pleaſure to the people, and the people loſt nothing, but laughed at their folly. The <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> anſwered. <hi>Lycurgus</hi> ſaw, felt, heard, or read ſome great damage that Ieſters and Players might doe in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, ſince againſt them hee eſtabliſhed ſo ſtraight a Law. But that which I know is; wee <hi>Greekes</hi> are better weeping with our Sages, then are the <hi>Romans</hi> laughing at their Fooles.</p>
               <p>Next doth M. <hi>Actor</hi> declare, that <hi>Cicero</hi> calleth <hi>Plautus,</hi> our <hi>Plautus,</hi> as it were noting thereby a name of excellency. Truth; hee calls him our <hi>Plautus</hi> in his workes <hi>de Republica</hi> by the mouth of <hi>Scipio.</hi> Concerning which, thus ſaith <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douicus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iues.</hi> Hee calleth him our <hi>Plautus,</hi> not that hee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer knew him, but becauſe hee was a Latine Poet, and hee had ſpoken of the Greekes before.</p>
               <p>Laſtly M. <hi>Actor</hi> maketh <hi>Cicero</hi> to commend vnto his ſonne <hi>Marcus</hi> ſome Poets, as <hi>Statius, Naeuius</hi> and <hi>Plautus</hi> for their writings. This is a thing hardly to be credited. For in the third of his <hi>Tuſculane</hi> Queſtions, ſpeaking of the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes corrupting the ſeeds of vertue, hee addeth Poets. Heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto (ſaith hee) alſo may Poets bee added, who pretending (what is not in them) a great deale of doctrine and wiſdome, are learnd, read, herd, and borne away in the mind of euery man. Now haue I ſufficiently confuted the particulars of M. <hi>Actors</hi> ſecond treatiſe of <hi>Actors antient dignity.</hi> Therefore I will now proceed in oppoſition thereof, to declare their antient indignity, and how baſe both Theaters, Play-Poets, Stage-Ieſters, and Actors were eſteemed of the cheeſe anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, which by any meanes could neuer well indure them.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3558:19"/>But mee thinkes I ſee how reſolutely paſt reaſon M. <hi>Actor,</hi> his mates and all adherents ſtand yet vppon their rermes of ancient dignity. Wherefore with Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> I ſay;<note place="margin">Aug. de Ciuit. Dei.</note> O that <hi>Scipto Naſsica</hi> were now aliue, hee whoſe face perhaps yee durſt not to behold! hee would ſhame you for this groſſe impudence of yours; For, what cauſe is there for you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claine at the proſperity of Chriſtian faith in theſe times, which condemneth the vſe of Playes, but onely that you would follow your luxury vncontrolled, and hauing remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the impediments of troubleſome oppoſition, ſwim on in your vnhoneſt &amp; vnhalowed diſſolution in ſeeking out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite variety of vain pleaſures, ſo to giue birth vnto theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitances, which wil heap thouſands of miſchiefes vpon you in the end? Hence it was, &amp; out of his moſt circumſpect zeale vnto his country, that the ſaid <hi>Scipio,</hi> who was then choſen by the Senate of thoſe times for the beſt man, without any difference of voices, (a thing worthy often repetition, when the Senate had giuen order for a Theater to bee built, wherein the Roman people might ſit and ſee plaies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scipio</hi> would haue no Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in Rome.</note> diſwaded their vaine reſolution, &amp; in a graue oration perſwaded them, not to ſuffer the luxury of the Greeks to creep into their old conditions: nor to conſent vnto the entry of forraigne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, to the ſubuerſion and extirpation of their natiue <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> perfection: working ſo much by his owne only Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that the whole bench of the iudicious Senate being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by his reaſons, expreſly prohibited the vſe of thoſe ſeats which the <hi>Romans</hi> began then to haue in the beholding of Playes.</p>
               <p>This Hiſtory <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> doth record. And how <hi>Naſſica</hi> ſo laboured with the Senate, that Theaters was held a thing vnfit, as preiudiciall to the manners of the people: ſo that by a decree of the Senate all the preparation for the Theater was laid aſide. And it was ordained that noe man ſhould place any ſeates, or ſit to behold any Playes, within the Citty, or within a mile of the walles. How erneſt would <hi>Scipio</hi> haue been to haue clenſed Rome of the Playes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3558:20"/>durſt ye haue oppoſed their authority whom he held for Gods being ignorant that they were malicious Diuels? or if hee knew it, then it ſeemes hee held (Oh helliſh igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) that they were rather to bee pleaſed, then deſpiſed, being hee was high Prieſt vnto them. For as yet that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly doctrine was not deliuered to the world, which puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the heart by ſaith, changeth the affect, and in <hi>Christ</hi> freeth men abſolutely, from the ſlauery of theſe proud and vngracious Diuels. Who as I haue before ſaid, euen by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and conſtraint forced the ſtayed Romans, which knew nothing but of armes before, to preſent them with ſuch thinges: nay (not only to preſent them but to dedicate and conſecrate them) ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> with all ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity vnto their honors.</p>
               <p>There are many thinges in this Hiſtory of eſpeciall note. Firſt that it was the choſen beſt man in Rome, which diſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Senate from their enterpriſe, and that the wiſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate condiſcended to him. Alſo that they held the Greekiſh corruption an enemy to the natiue Roman perfection: which afterward proued true when they had giuen entrance to it. The laſt thing is that they baniſhed Theaters out of their Citty, and without a mile of their walles: which was euer after obſerued vntill the ſack of Corinth, when <hi>Lucius Memmius</hi> ſet vp a Theater for the Playes at his triumph, which ſtood no longer neither then the triumphs laſted, nor any after it till <hi>Pompeius</hi> time. For as long as meerely ſome <hi>Atomes</hi> of Roman perfection did remaine, ſtanding Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by no meanes might be erected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caligula,</hi> that famous, or rather infamous villaine, what impudent ſhifts he made to maintaine his riot, all Hiſtories of him do record. Among other thinges hee ſhamefully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted toll and cuſtome from Baudes, Harlots, and ſtrumpets which vſe may ſeeme was euer after retained till <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> was Emperor. For hee, ſaith <hi>Lampridius;</hi> did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that it ſhould bee brought into the common treaſure, but aſſigned it to the reparations of the Theaters. By which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3558:20"/>it is euident how baſely he eſteemed them, that the moſt baſe of all gaines, and what hee thought vnhoneſt for him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, he aſſigned to the Theaters, which ſo many Baudes, Varlets and Harlots both then and now did haunt.</p>
               <p>Concerning Poets, <hi>Polidorus Virgill</hi> ſaith. That a little aſter <hi>Ennius</hi> his time, Poetry was ſo debaſed and held in ſuch deſpite, that if any one had profeſſed himſelfe to bee a Poet, hee was taken for a murtherer or a Ruffian, What the Romans held concerning Poeſie and Commedians, <hi>Cicero</hi> recordeth in his booke of the common wealth where <hi>Scipio</hi> is brought in ſaying thus. <hi>If that the priueledge of an old cuſtome had not allowed them, Comedians could neuer haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuch proofes of their vilenes vpon Theaters.</hi> Hee procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth further and ſheweth what Lawes were made againſt them in the twelue tables, and that our liues ſhould not be cenſured by Poets, but by lawfull Magiſtrates, and in the end concludes, that the ancient Romans diſliked, that <hi>any mans life ſhould be praiſed or diſpraiſed vpon the ſtage:</hi> and would by no meanes haue their manners to be liable to the quips and cenſures of Poets, but inflicted a Capitall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vppon ſuch as durſt offend in that kind. And ſo the Poets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eauing to taxe the vices of the Citty, turned their pens to worſer matters, (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirmes) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and publiſh the filthineſſe, obſcoenity and villanies of the Gods. In another place of that Booke <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, <hi>They held the art of ſtage-playing ſo baſe and vnmanly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">No Players capable of honor in Rome, not ſo much as their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note> that <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they did not only detains all the honors of the Citty from ſuch hind of men, but appointed the Cenſors in their viewes to remoue them from being any part of any tribe, and would not vouchſafe them to be counted as members of the Citty.</hi> Then it muſt of force bee granted that the Players were the moſt pernicious men of conditions that could be, and the vildeſt in their villanies, becauſe they could not bee allowed for Cittizens in that Citty, which harbord ſo many thouſands of wicked and vngratious fellowes, all as Cittizens; in ſo much that by the ancient fathers; <hi>Rome</hi> was called <hi>Babilon</hi> in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3558:21"/>weſt. That Players were excluded from being of any tribe, <hi>Liuy</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius</hi> do both teſtifie: vnleſſe authority made them ſuch, for that ſeemes as a conſtraint. As befell to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus Laberius,</hi> whom <hi>Nero</hi> requeſted to act a <hi>mimick</hi> of his vppon the Stage: and yet hee neuertheleſſe was after that a Gentleman of Rome. For hee that is forced to offend the Law, is held not to offend. But a right worthy decree, and well beſeeming the Roman wiſedome was this. That none which would chooſe of a Roman Cittizen to become a Player, ſhould only bee ſecluded all honors, but by the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> cenſure bee made vtterly vncapable of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uing as a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his proper tribe. But why were their Players ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed, by whom their Gods were ſo pleaſed? This was the Controuerſie betweene the Greekes and the Romans. The Greekes thought good reaſon to honour thoſe Players, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they muſt honour them which did require thoſe Playes: but the Romans diſabled their Players to beare honor in their Citty.</p>
               <p>The Greekes mad a Law that the <hi>Comedians</hi> might ſpeake what they liſt of any man: The Romans made a law for the abridgement of ſuch licentious liberty; and gaue them leaue to ſay what they would of their Diuell-Gods. The Greeks ſeeing they had ſuch Gods to ſerue as required Playes, thought it not fit to take away any liberty from the Poets in vſing theſe Stage-mocks and ſhames. And this they did for feare leaſt ther Gods ſhould bee prouoked to anger againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, in caſe they went about to make themſelues into more honeſt moulds then they were, and ſoe ſeeme to preferre themſelues before them, which delighted in the Poeticall fictions of their vicious facts: or els for deſire to bee made like their Gods, euen in their greateſt enormities. And from this immagined conuenience came it, that they held the very actors of thoſe Playes worthy of their citties honors. As weread that <hi>Eſchines</hi> of <hi>Athens</hi> (whom <hi>Demosthenes</hi> in his oration <hi>de Corona</hi> calls an <hi>apiſh Tragedian</hi>) hauing beene an actor of Tragedies in his youth, is ſaid to haue borne
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3558:21"/>office in the common wealth. Yet <hi>Aeſchines</hi> himſelfe in an Epiſtle he wrote to the Athenians, ſeemes to affirme, that hee had giuen ouer his ſtage-playing before hee bare any place in the Citty. But on the other ſide the Romans were ſo farre from gracing them, that they would not alow them in place in a Plebeyan tribe: much leſſe in the Court or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, but held them diſgracefull to all callings. <hi>Plato</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting of the true perfection of a Citty, would haue Poets baniſhed from that ſociety, as enemies to the Citties full perfection being wel ordered. Yet in his 10. Book <hi>de Repub. Socrates</hi> hauing ſpoken much againſt them, concludeth all in this: that hee holds that Poetry fit to bee excluded, which giues life to vnmanly affections: and that to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, which is manly and honeſt. For all Poetry is not to bee condemned: they are called by ſome a diuine kinde of men, namely when they ſing hymnes to the Deitie: as <hi>Dauid</hi> in his Pſalmes, <hi>Solomon</hi> in his Canticles, and the Prophets in their pleaſant Pſalmodies. And if they exceed not in looſeneſſe, yeeld not to rancor, conſent not to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, byte not with taunts, ſcoffes, quips, and ieſts, ſet not abroch fables, fictions, lyes, wanton toyes, amorous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, nor in their Poeſies ſow any ſeeds of corruption, ſuch Poets are profitable members in <hi>Plato's</hi> Common-wealth. But ſuch good Poets, Play-Poets in theſe daies are not: and if they will be Play-poets, then to pleaſe their hearers ſuch they cannot be. And therefore are they vnneceſſarie in a common-wealth. <hi>Archilochus</hi> the Poet as ſoone as he came into Sparta, was preſently thruſt out againe, becauſe hee had written falſhood in his Poems: and euer after, the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> forbad all fabulous Poeſie. And hence grew the common prouerbs. <hi>Poets are lyars.</hi> And <hi>Poets and Painters may lye by authoritie.</hi> And it was written of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> that he was but ill or ſlenderly brought vp in Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, becauſe hee loued the truth. And a man might ſay, that this mooued <hi>Caligula</hi> to condemne <hi>Virgils</hi> and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3558:22"/>
                  <hi>Homers</hi> Bookes, becauſe of their prophane fables. The Citty of <hi>Marſeles</hi> hath beene marueilouſly praiſed in ancient time, for that ſhee alwaies reiected ſtage-Poets &amp; Players. And the Emperors <hi>Tiberius, Anthony, Aurelius, Frederick</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Henry</hi> the third cauſed them to be driuen out of their Empire, and the Tribunes baniſhed one <hi>Naeuius</hi> out of Rome. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> likewiſe baniſhed <hi>Ouid,</hi> and <hi>Domitian Iuuenal, Archilochus</hi> fell into confuſion by his owne detractions. <hi>Plato</hi> compared the diſputes in Poetry to the banquets of the ignorant, that vſe muſicke inſteed of good diſcouſe. <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſaid that their ſoules hanged in Hell vppon a tree, ſtill pulled on euery ſide by ſerpents for their damnable inuentions. <hi>Suetonius Tranquillius</hi> in the life of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> declareth, that in Rome there was a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ieſting-Plaier called <hi>Epifanius,</hi> who to ſhew the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour pleaſure, and hoping to haue a good reward, went to the Pallace at one time in the attire of a Page, and at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time in the habit of a Roman matron: and ſo truely counterfeited euery thing, that it ſeemed to bee the very perſons whom he acted. But the Emperour was ſo highly diſpleaſed with what the Actor had done, that forthwith he commanded him to be whipt about the Theater three times. And when he complained, that the Emperour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vagabonds to be whipt but once, and he thrice. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> anſwered; Thou art worſe then a Vagabond; once they ſhal whip thee for the iniury thou haſt don to the perſons thou didſt repreſent, the ſecond time for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption thou hadſt to act thy folly in my preſence, and thirdly for the time thou haſt loſt, and made others to looſe in beholding and hearing. <hi>Don Antony de Gueuara</hi> in his <hi>diall of Princes</hi> hath this Hiſtory. That in Rome their ieſters &amp; Comedians became ſo diſſolute, that they were occaſion of ſlander among the people. Which ſcene and conſidered, and withall that they liued as loyterers and fooles: the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of Rome determined amongſt themſelues to baniſh them all out of the common-wealth. On this execution of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3558:22"/>theſe loyterers, ſprung diuers diſſentions among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For the Princes which were good caſt them out, and thoſe which were euill called them in. So that one of the tokens to know a vertuous or vicious Prince in Rome, was to ſee whether hee maintained theſe Players among the people. <hi>Cornelius Tacitus annalium lib.</hi> 1. Recordeth that in the Raigne of <hi>Tiberius</hi> there was a very great ſedition in Rome, by reaſon of the Players licentiouſneſſe. And after he hath ſhewed the Ryot which by their meanes was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, he ſaith. <hi>Actum eſt de eaſeditione apud Patres, dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banturque ſententiae, vt Praetoribus ius virgarum in Hiſtriones eſſet. It was debated among the Senators concerning that ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their ſentence of it was: That there was a law for the praetors, to make the Players taſte of the whipping poſt.</hi> By this we may ſee that the Romane Hiſtrions or players, were not onely excluded all honors, euen the leaſt that might bee in the Citie, as is before declared: but they were alſo coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Rogues, vpon any offence ſubiect to the laſh of the whip. Like vnto which by the lawes of this Realm of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land alſo they were muſtred in the Catalogue of the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall kindes of Rogues and Vagabonds, and ought ſo to be puniſhed, whereſoeuer they be taken, if they had their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts: ſuch as trauell the countries with playes and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes, making a trade of it: As oftentimes our London Players when the infection is in the Citie make an occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in trauelling the Countreys and ranging from Fayre to Fayre and from Citie to Citie. And what difference is there between the one ſort &amp; the other, but euen none at all? For both alike excheat mony fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the communaltie, &amp; for round ſummes of ſiluer giue them nothing but multitudes of vain and fooliſh words. Thus haue I ſufficiently prooued out of good Hiſtorie the indignitie wherewith Play-Poets, Players, and Theaters were branded by the wiſeſt men, and greateſt Princes of the world.</p>
               <q>Quipergit quae vult dicere, audret quae non vuli?</q>
               <trailer>The end of the Second Booke.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="book">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3558:23"/>
               <head>A Refutation of the Apology for <hi>Actors: And of the wonderfull abuſe</hi> of their impious qualitie.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE THIRD BOOKE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto haue I proceeded in Refutation and oppoſition of Maſter <hi>Actors Apologie:</hi> Omitting nothing worthy of notice, which I haue not touched, or ſhall not touch in this my laſt treatiſe. And now that I haue declared the abhominable originall, with Ancient and preſent indignitie of Players; I come laſtly to handle the vſe of their qualitie: wherein according to my former method, after I haue conuinced M. <hi>Actors</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and affirmations, with Reaſons and negations: I will ſet downe the moſt abhominable abuſe, and impious qualitie of them.</p>
               <p>Tragedies and Comedies ſaith he, out of <hi>Donatus,</hi> had their beginning <hi>a Rebus Diuinis,</hi> from Diuine ſacrifices. It's true; they were firſt inſtituted of Diuels and for Diuels, and therefore as things firſt conſecrated to Diuels, ought to be abandoned.</p>
               <p>Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> ſets downe his definition of a Comedie: for which hee ſhould haue alledged his Author, becauſe he ſaith it is according to the Latins. But ſuppoſe it were of his owne braine gathered from <hi>Ciceroes</hi> ſaying (I know not where) which he afterward alledgeth thus: A Comedy is the Image of truth. Well then; to diſprooue his definition I muſt confute <hi>Cicero:</hi> And that thus.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3558:23"/>
               <p>Whatſoeuer is the Image of truth, is like vnto truth. For Images are ſaid to be like vnto what they repreſent.</p>
               <p>But a Comedieis not like vnto truth:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo:</hi> It is not the Image of Truth.</p>
               <p>My Aſſumption I confirme thus. A Comedy is not like vnto truth, becauſe it is wholly compoſed of Fables and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and Fables and Vanities, are lyes and deceipts: and lyes and deceipts are cleane contrarie to truth, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlike it, euen as vertue is vnlike to vice. Wherefore my Aſſumption being true my concluſion is alſo firme. But beſide this refutation of his Definition, I will lay downe another in oppoſition of it, gathered out of the workes of <hi>Atheneiu:</hi> Thus Playes are the fruit of vintage and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, conſiſting of ſundry impieties,<note place="margin">Definition of Playes.</note> comprehending euill and damnable things, wherein is taught how in our liues and manners wee may follow all kinde of vice with Art. For they are full of filthy words and geſtures,<note place="margin">The riches of Playes,</note> ſuch as would not become very lacques and Courtezans: and haue ſundry inuentions which infect the ſpirit, and repleniſh it with vnchaſte, whooriſh, coſening, deceitfull, wanton and miſchieuous paſsions: beſides which inconueniences Stage-Players doe oftentimes enuy, and gnaw at the honor of an other, and to pleaſe the vulgar people, ſet before them lyes, and teach much diſſolution and deceitfulnes: by this meanes turning vpſide downe all diſcipline and good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Herevpon <hi>Tully</hi> complaineth all in vaine, who being to ſpeak of Comedians and Poets, when he came to them ſaith: <hi>The clamer and approbation of the people, when it is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with theſe Poeticall fictions, as the testimony of ſome great and learned matter, oh what darkneſſe doth it inuolue a man in? what feares it inflicts, what lust it inflames?</hi> Thus S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alledgeth the ſentence. But the whole ſentence I take it is out of the third of <hi>Cicero's Tuſculane Queſtions</hi> where ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the cauſes which corrupt the ſeeds of virtue natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſowne in vs, he ſaith. Heervnto alſo Poets may be added,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3558:24"/>who pretending a great deale of doctrine and wiſedome, are learned, read, heard and borne away in the mind of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man. But when that great maiſter the multitude is added alſo, and the whole company ſwarming on euery ſide vnto vices, then chiefly are wee infected with depraued opinion, and drawne from our very expreſſe nature.</p>
               <p>Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> recites a verſe againſt them which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne Playes.</p>
               <q>Oderunt hilarem tristes, triſtem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iocoſi.</q>
               <p>It is true; for grauity and leuity, two contraries cannot conſiſt in one. But what ſaid the Lacedemonian concerning this. <hi>I know we Greeks are better weeping with our Sages: then are the Romans laughing at their fooles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this hee will ſeeme to anſwer an obiection, which becauſe it is but a peece of an obiection, extorted, both it and his anſwere I will omit. The obiection is, that the Romanes in their time, and ſome in theſe dayes haue abuſed Playes: but they hauenot only abuſed them, for they are abuſe it ſelfe, (as I ſhall inſtance further heereafter) and euer were.</p>
               <p>After this againe hee ſaith.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Playes are in vſe as they are vnderſtood:</l>
                  <l>Spectators eyes may make them bad or good.</l>
               </q>
               <p>O right excellently well ſaid! In what a doubtfull caſe would the vſe of playes then ſtand, if none but fooles (as common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they all are) or none but blindmen were their auditors? the one kind could not vnderſtand, the other could not ſee, and conſequently neither giue right iudgement of them: For the one could not vnderſtand what vice to auoid, the other could not ſee acted to the life what magnanimious vertue for to follow.</p>
               <p>But to leaue this forked argument, and with more plaine reaſons to touch his meaning. I Deny his maxime. For all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this <hi>Axiome. Omne accipitur ſecundum modum acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientis</hi> bee true, euery thing is receiued according to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of that which receaueth: yet it extendeth it ſelf not ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3558:24"/>farre as M. <hi>Actors</hi> intention. For then according to the diſcretion of fooles and blind men, if Playes were euill, (as they are not to be thought otherwiſe) by their good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of them they were good; which how abſurd a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it is let all men iudge. Beſides which if their were any good in Playes, yet for the euill, which is greater, they are not tollerable. And wee are taught not to doe good if any euill may enſue thereby. For good when it is the occaſion of euill, ceaſeth any longer to bee good, but is turned into ſinne: For euill, and the occaſion of euill are vnder the ſame predicament of ſinne.</p>
               <p>Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> inferreth many vocations and inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of life wherein men liue, amongſt which there hath beene ſome bad: and thereupon demaundeth, whether the generall ſhall be condemned for the particulars ſake. I anſwer no; But the <hi>Genus</hi> of playes comes not vnder the protection of this reaſon, becauſe they are wholy euill, as more at large I will ſhew towards the end of my diſcourſe. Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> proceeds in the vſe of Playes, and ſhewes firſt that they are an Ornament to the Citty. But I thinke the ſaying of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius Maximus</hi> of more authority then this: who ſaith, Playes were neuer brought vp <hi>Sine Regni rubore,</hi> without ſhame to the Kingdome. Secondly, hee ſheweth (and to the diſgrace of his mother-tongue) that our Engliſh was the rudeſt language in the world, a Gally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mafry of Dutch, French, Iriſh, Saxon, Scotch, and Welſh, but by Play-Poets it hath beene refined. But doth he not forget, that whiles they adde Greeke, Lattine, and Italian, they make a great mingle-mangle. Nay, before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt by Baſtard <hi>William</hi> that the French came in, our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh tongue was moſt perfect, able to expreſſe any Hebru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme, which is the tryall of perfection in Languages, and now it will very hardly expound a Greeke Lecture. For after that the French had once corrupted it, it was but of late yeares that it could recouer a common Dialect againe. Since which againe it hath indeed beene more refined, but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3558:25"/>thereby it is become more obſcure, and vſed amongſt few, for the ſimple vulgar people cannot vnderſtand it: And a plaine man can ſcarce vtter his mind, for want of Phraſes, (as I may ſay) according to the faſhion. But what refined<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is in our language, it's not from Poets, but from other learned mens writings, from whom they borrow all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined words they haue.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he affirmes that Playes haue taught the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant knowledge of many famous Hiſtories. They haue indeed made many to know of thoſe Hiſtories they neuer did, by reaſon they would neuer take the paines to reade them. But theſe that know the Hiſtories before they ſee them acted, are euer aſhamed, when they haue heard what lyes the Players inſert amongſt them, and how greatly they depraue them. If they be too long for a Play, they make them curtals; if too ſhort, they enlarge them with many Fables, and whither too long or too ſhort, they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them with a Foole and his Bables: whereby they make them like Leaden rules, which men will fit to their worke, and not frame their worke to them. So that the ignorant inſtead of true Hiſtory ſhall beare away nothing but fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous lyes.</p>
               <p>Next M. <hi>Actor</hi> hath ſtriued wonderfully, in ſhewing the particular vſes of playes, which I will reſerue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, with all their qualities, toward the latter end of this book, And proceed next to ſhew the abſurdities of M. <hi>Actor</hi> in his 3. Hiſtories of ſtrange accidents that haue happened at playes: which make more againſt him then for him, if they were well conſidered, according to Gods iuſt iudgement, and not M. Actor's vaine application. The firſt and laſt Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory concerning treacherous murthers committed by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſty wiues vpon their husbands, hee applyeth to playes, becauſe at plaies their firſt diſcoueries were intimated.</p>
               <p>But it was farre otherwiſe, for theſe bloody-minded wines lay long in their ſinnes without repentance, God for a great while vſing mercy and patience towards them: But when he
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3558:25"/>ſaw them to perſiſt in their inflexible ſtubburnneſſe, that in ſtead of ſuing to him for grace and remiſſion of their ſinnes, they prouoked him to greater anger, and in ſtead of coming to the temple there to pray, to haunt Sathans Sinagogue there to ſee ſport and ſeed their pleaſures: hee euen tooke them napping in the Diuells Sanctuary: that where they thought to conceiue much mirth from vanity, there they might bee prickt in conſcience, and receiue the beginning of their ſorrow, at laſt to bring them to repentance, that God might ſaue their ſoules, though in his iuſtice hee brought their bodies to deſtruction. The other Hiſtory of the flight of ſome rouing <hi>Spaniards</hi> from a towne in Cornewall, vpon ſtriking vp of an alarme at night by the Players on the ſtage, hee applyeth likewiſe vnto playes. But farre rather it is to bee attributed to Gods mercy, who carefully kept watch for the towne and not the Players. Hee I ſay, while they were ſecure at their pleaſures, and feared leaſt when they had greateſt cauſe, turned their preſent enterlude to a good vſe, being euill of it ſelfe (as ſometimes hee vſeth the Diuels themſelues for his inſtruments) thereby to teach them to be more wary another time, and not to entertaine againe the cauſe of like ſecurity: and ſparing the towne, for the good that were abſent, and not ruinating it for the vicious min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that were preſent at theſe Players trumperies.</p>
               <p>Now haue I oppoſed and confuted the grand Arguments of M. <hi>Actors</hi> third booke, ſuch as concerne ſome, though not the more particular vſe of Playes, which now I come generally to handle. Before which yet euen as M. <hi>Actor</hi> hath done, ſo will I declare two authentick Hiſtories of fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full accidents that haue happened at the Theaters. The firſt is recorded in the booke intituled, <hi>The Anotomy of Abuſes.</hi> made by M. <hi>Phillip Stubbes,</hi> that when a great multitude were aſſembled at the Theater, the Lord ſent a mighty earthquake as though all would haue fallen about their eares.</p>
               <p>Whereat the people ſore amazed, fomeleapt downe to the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3558:26"/>ground from the tops of turrets and galleries where they ſate: whereof ſome had their legges broke, ſome their armes, ſome their backes, ſome hurt one where, and ſome another, and many ſore cruſht and bruiſed, but not any which went not away ſore affraid, and wounded in conſcience.</p>
               <p>The Second hiſtory I haue both read and heard. Read, if I be not deceaued in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ines</hi> commentaries vpon Saint <hi>Augustine:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Another more fearefull acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent at a Play.</note> and heard ſome fiue yeares ſince at <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> from the mouth of a Reuerend Preacher, recited there in a ſet Sermon againſt the abuſe of Playes. And it was thus. In the times of the primatiue Church, a Chriſtian woman went into the Theater to behold the plaies. She entred in well and ſound, but ſhe returned and came forth poſſeſſed of the Diuell. Wherevpon certaine Godly brethren de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Sathan how he durſt be ſo bould, as to enter into her a Chriſtian. Whereto he anſwered, that <hi>hee found her in his owne houſe,</hi> and therefore tooke poſſeſſion of her as his owne. A fearefull example this is indeede, able to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighten and deter any from entring into Theaters, leaſt they incur the like danger as this woman did. But now I am come to entreat of the qualities of Plaies and Players, I will heare add ſome hiſtoricall Apothegmes and ſayings concerning them, vnto the former recited and alleaged in my ſecond treatiſe, and ſo withall I will proceed in my diſcourſe. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his booke of the <hi>City of God,</hi> ſpeaking of ſome vices in the <hi>Romaines</hi> which their Cities ruine, by the <hi>Barbarian Gothes,</hi> did not reforme, exclaymeth thus. O you ſenceleſſe men! how are you bewitched not with error but furor? That when all the nations in the Eaſt (as we heare) bewaile your Citties ruine, and all the moſt remote regions bewaile your miſery, and publike ſorrow, you your ſelues runne headlong vnto the Theaters: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them, filling them, and playing farre madder parts now then euer you did before. This your plague of minde, this your wracke of honeſty, was that which <hi>Scipio</hi> ſo fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red when hee would not haue any Theaters built for you.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:3558:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dio,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Tyaian</hi> reporteth concerning an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Player thus, That when they entreated the good Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour that hee would pleaſe to heare him; hee anſwered. It is not for the maieſty of a graue and vertuous Prince, that in his preſence any ſuch vaine thing ſhould be ſhewed. For in ſuch a cafe himſelf ſhould be no leſſe noted of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then the other accused of folly. And further he ſaid. Before Princes a man ſhould not be ſo hardy to ſpeake diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt words, nor ſhew light repreſentations. And in ſuch a caſe as much paine deſerue they which moue him thereto, as thoſe which doe repreſent them, for none ought to put before Princes things that might allure them to vices, but ſuch as might moue them to vertues. <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> wrote a letter to <hi>Lambertus</hi> his friend, certifying him that he had baniſhed from <hi>Rome,</hi> all Ieſters, Fooles, and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Players, and declaring how hee had found the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers of many learned Philoſophers in <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto he had ſent them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Marcus Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius <hi>his letter.</hi>
                  </note>Some fragments of this letter I will heare repeat. After ſalutation ſaith hee. To declare the chiefe cauſe that I write vnto thee at this preſent, it is. I ſend thee three ſhips loaden with Ieſters, Fooles, Players, and Vagabunds. And yet I doe not ſend vnto thee all the Vagabunds which are in <hi>Rome,</hi> for then I ſhould em-people thine Ile with ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. The offices that they bare was, that ſome of them were Rayling ieſters, ſome Singers of Mallicious and filthy ſongs, others playd common playes, and enterludes, and entertayned the <hi>Romaines</hi> with fooliſh fables and tales, others ſet forth vaine and light bookes of Poeſie. And yet I ſweare vnto thee theſe Loyterers wanted no Fooles to heare them. I let thee weet my friend <hi>Lambert,</hi> that theſe loyterers are ſuch, and their ſchollers in number ſo many, that though the maiſters may be in three ſhips car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, yet the ſchollers in an hundred could not be tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. One thing there is at which I much wonder: that the Earth-quakes ouerthrow the houſes, great invndations
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3558:27"/>carry away the bridges, the froſt periſh the vines, and the contagious aire infecteth Wiſe-men: But yet there is no plague that conſumeth theſe Fooles. O <hi>Rome</hi> how vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py doſt thou preſent thy ſelfe to him that doth diligently ſearch thee. For in thee wanteth valliant Captaines, honeſt Senators, iuſt Cenſors, faithfull Officers, vertuous Princes, and onely thou aboundeſt with Fooles, Ieſters, Players, Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, and Vagabonds. O <hi>Lambert,</hi> what ſeruice ſhouldeſt thou doe to God, and Profit to our Mother <hi>Rome,</hi> if for three ſhips of Fooles thou dideſt returne vs one onely Barke of Wiſe-men.</p>
               <p>After this hee writeth of thoſe that heare theſe Fooles, thus. A Foole hath a ſemblance of the Sage when he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companieth with a Sage: But the Sage ſheweth himſelfe a Foole when he accompanieth with a Foole. If wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with Lyers wee ſhallbe Lyers, and if wee deſire the Fooliſh we ſhall be Fooles: for accordying to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Doctrines we haue, ſuch ſhalbe the Sciences we learne, and the workes we ſhall follow. <hi>Dioniſus</hi> the <hi>Scici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> tyrant demanded of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> with what perſons wee ſhould deuide our goods: who anſwered, with aged per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ſhould counſaile vs, good ſeruants which ſhould obey vs, friends that ſhould comfort vs, and the poore that ſhould pray for vs. By this anſwere wee may ſee, that it is not iuſt to giue to cate to Ieſters, Players, Loyterers, and Fooles. And it ſeemeth to me, a man ought not to thinke that Players can giue good inſtruction by their lyes and mockeries. Alſo it ſhould be great folly to vſe ſuch men as Sages, which of their owne will haue made them-ſelues Fooles. And againe it ſeemeth to me vaine to thinke, that ſuch Ieſters ſhould ſerue as ſeruants. For they to fly trauaile haue onely taken vpon them this ſo ſlanderous an office. Thirdly, it ſeemeth to me a thing of great inconuenience, that a noble or Sage man ſhould accept any ſuch Ieſter as his friend: For they cannot be counted amongſt true friends, ſince they loue vs not for the vertue we poſſeſſe, but
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3558:27"/>for the goods which wee haue. Fourthly it ſeemeth vnto me vninſt that vnder the coulour of pouerty it ſhould bee law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to giue meat to ſuch loyterers: For wee cannot ſay they are pore becauſe they want ritches but becauſe they abound in folly. Since therefore they are not honeſt poore, true friendes, faithfull ſeruants, wiſe Sages, therefore it is folly for any man to ſpend his goods vppon them, and thereby become defamed.</p>
               <p>By this Centurion thou ſhalt know all thinges that are chanced among the priſoners. For if I ſhould write vnto thee the whole matter as it was done, it would bee much paine to me to write it and to thee very tedious to read. It ſufficeth preſently to ſay, that the day of the great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of the mother <hi>Berecinth,</hi> a great ſlander aroſe in Rome by reaſon of theſe ieſters, players and loyterers. And by the faith of a good man I ſweare vnto thee, that the bloodſhed throughout all places, ſurmounted the wine which was drunke at the feaſt. And as thou knoweſt the Cittizens are come to ſo great impudency, that hee which on that day dranke moſt, was eſteemed to haue offered the greateſt ſacrifice. I am yet affraid to remember the cruelties which that day I beheld with my own eyes, but I am much more aſhamed of that which they talke of vs in ſtrange Realmes. Then ſaw I Rome, inuincible to the valiant men, that day ouercome with loyterers. Rome, which could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be won by the Carthaginians, is now won by Ieſters, Players and Vagabonds: Rome, which triumphed ouer all the Realmes is now vanquiſhed by ſuch idle perſons: Finally I ſaw Rome, which in times paſt gaue lawes to the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, now become the ſlaue of fooles. In this caſe I haue beene ſo troubled that I cannot tell what to ſay, and leſſe what to write to thee. One thing comforteth me, that ſince Rome and her Romans do not reioyce themſelues but with fooles, that ſhee and her children bee not puniſhed but by the handes of fooles. I think not in this caſe that the Gods do any wrong, if Rome, which laughed at the ieſts of Playes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3558:28"/>do weepe one day with the loyterers in good earneſt. Thou mightſt demand of me <hi>Lambert,</hi> ſince we Princes are bound to maiutaine equall iuſtice to all, wherefore wee diſſemble the offences of others performed in earneſt, and yet we will not pardon theſe loyterers, ſince all their inuentions was but in ieſt for mirth and paſtime. I promiſe thee though their offences were great indeed, yet doe I not baniſh them ſo much for the blood they haue ſhed, as for the good orders they haue peruerted. And once againe I proteſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee that I haue not baniſhed them ſo much becauſe they were occaſion of murthers, as becauſe they were teachers of lyes. Without compariſon greater is the offence to God and greater the damage to the common wealth, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as theſe loyterers haue done, the ſences of wiſe men, then that which the murtherers haue done in bereaning their aduerſaries of life. The end of theſe ieſters, players, idle men and vagabonds, is alwayes to perſwade men that they ſpeake and treat continually in mockeries, to rid them of melancholly and ſorrow, and giue them recreation: and all this is but to deceiue them of their goods. In which caſe I wiſh it would ſo pleaſe God, that they did but ſpoyle vs onely of our goods, without depriuing vs of our wiſe-dome.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Scipio Affricanus</hi> had ended the warres of <hi>Affrick,</hi> hee went through <hi>Rome,</hi> accompanied, not with valiant Captaines, but with Players: Which when a Philoſopher eſpied, he ſaid vnto him theſe wordes. O <hi>Scipio</hi> according to the much I haue heard of thee, and the little I ſee in thee, it were better thou hadſt dyed in <hi>Affrick</hi> then haue come to <hi>Rome.</hi> For thy worthy and thy honorable acts in thy ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence did aſtoniſh vs, but thy leuity in our preſence doth offend vs. To thee it is great infamy, and a ſhame vnto the ſacred Senate, that thou hauing conquered ſo many mighty Princes in <hi>Affrick,</hi> ſhouldſt goe accompanied with fooles and madmen in <hi>Rome.</hi> O <hi>Scipio,</hi> thy life had not then ſoe much perill among thine enemies, as thine honor hath at
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3558:28"/>this preſent among fooles. After that theſe loyterers and vaga bonds ſhall land in thine lle, thou ſhalt depriue them of none of their goods, but thou ſhalt not ſuffer them to bee ſo hardy to exerciſe their crafts: which if they preſume to do they ſhall put them to death. Wee that are Sages call them fooles: yet are they ſubtill fooles which by craft liue vppon the ſweat of others.</p>
               <p>And with greater reaſon ſhould they mock our works, then wee laugh at their words: for they profit more of our goods then wee can of their folly.</p>
               <p>Afterwards ſpeaking of the plague when playes were firſt induced, he imprecateth thus. Would to the immortall Gods that the plague had ended thoſe few which remained, before this curſed generation had brought ſuch abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cuſtomes into <hi>Rome.</hi> Much better had it beene for our Mother <hi>Rome</hi> ſhee had beene diſpeopled, then ſuch raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calls had been her inhabitants.</p>
               <p>Since the time I was borne, I neuer ſaw any thing leſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable in the common wealth, nor more vaine, nor worſe inuentions, nor coulder recreations then theſe are, which theſe ieſters and players do inuent. What thing can be more monſtrous then to ſee the mockery of a foole draw many wiſe men beſide their wittes? what greater folly then to eſteeme the ieſts of a foole worth the laſter of the Sage? what greater cruelty in Rome, then that rich men giue more to a Player for one houres babling, then to a ſeruant for his whole yeares trauaile? What greater theft then this, that the Gariſons in <hi>Hiria</hi> want, but Players ieſtars and loyterers in Rome haue too much? what greater ſhame to Rome then this: that Players haue wonne more by their enterludes and mockeries, then diuers Captaines with their weapons and triumphes?</p>
               <p>Afterwards hee ſheweth to how great abundance of wealth ſome Players haue come: wherevppon hee ſaith thus. Behold <hi>Lambert</hi> how they are neglected of the Gods and fauored of Fortune: and in how little eſtimation the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3558:29"/>goods of this life ought to bee, ſince ſome by counterfeiting leaue behind them as great memory of their folly, as others in truth doe by their wiſedome. One thing onely there is of theſe loyterers that pleaſeth me. That with their preſence at Rome, they made euery man laugh at their fooleries: and now they are baniſhed all remaine ſad for the mony they carried away. It is a iuſt iudgement of God, that thoſe which haue taken vaine pleaſure together, do weep afterwards for their loſſe ſeuerally, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> telleth of a <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> who when hee was demanded what he thought of <hi>Tirteus</hi> the Poet anſwered; Hee was very good to infect young mens wits. And <hi>Hieron</hi> of <hi>Syracuſa</hi> condemned the Poet <hi>Epicarinus</hi> in a great fine, becauſe in his wiues preſence he had repeated laſciuious verſes. If this ſhould be obſerued in theſe times, Poets would verily make too true the common ſaying which calleth them <hi>Thred-bare. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iues</hi> alſo writeth, that <hi>Ouid</hi> was moſt iuſtly baniſhed as an inſtrument of wantonneſſe, for making loue bookes, enterludes, and ſuch amorous trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> an ancient Doctor of the Church, called Poets and certaine Philoſophers the Patriarches of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. And in his booke <hi>De Speculo</hi> ſaith, that Playes were conſecrate to the Idoll <hi>Bacchus,</hi> becauſe hee found out and inuented ſtrong drinke, which <hi>Palingenius</hi> toucheth at in theſe verſes concerning Poets.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hi furijs agitantur Iacobi, &amp; Apolinis aeſtro,</l>
                  <l>Quorum ego iudicium falſum, &amp; damnabile duco.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Blondus</hi> in his booke <hi>de Roma triumphante</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Romaines</hi> gaue lawes to their Ieſters and Players, euen as they did diſcipline to their mattiall Cheeftaines. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other Lawes hee repeateth theſe three of eſpeciall note. Firſt they permitted none to vſe ſuch feats vnleſſe hee had ſome other Craft to liue by: But our Players are altogether idle. Secondly they prohibited any vice to be
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3558:29"/>ſo bold in his oſtentations as to ſpeake malliciouſly: but this is the chiefe ſubiect of our Commedies now. Laſtly they ordayned that for no paſtime ſhewed, or other thing ſpoken, they ſhould be ſo bould to take any mony; and to that end allowed them a ſmall penſion out of the treaſury. If our Players and Ieſters ſhould be enioyned to this rule, I am perſwaded their gaines would be no eye-ſore to them at the yeares end: For the country loueth them not ſo well as to giue them yearely penſions, except a Noble man or ſo, haue ſome as reteyners to them. But they may here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the ſaying of <hi>Bias. To be accounted a noble mans ieſter, is to be eſteemed a mercinary Foole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the end of his eight booke of <hi>Politicques,</hi> debarreth all youth acceſſe to playes, leaſt in ſeeking to quench the thirſt of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> they quench it with a pottle of fire. <hi>Lactantius,</hi> a learned father, ſaith, <hi>Hiſtrionú impudiſsimi geſtus nihil aliud niſi libidinem mouent.</hi> The ſhameleſſe geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Players ſerue to nothing ſo much as to moue the fleſh to luſt and vncleaneſſe. Saint <hi>Chriſostome</hi> calleth plaies <hi>feſia Sathanae,</hi> feaſts of the Diuell. And in his Seuenteene homily vpon Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> hee ſaith. There is no perrill vpon the ſea ſo dangerous, as are the Theaters and places of Comedies and Plaies, and declareth at large what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutneſſe, diſorder, factions, miſchiefes and inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces haue enſued thereby. Saint <hi>Auguſtine de Ciuit. Dei</hi> hath written his whole ſecond booke againſt them, and ſaith, <hi>Pecunias histrionibus dare, vitium eſt inane, non virtus.</hi> To giue mony vnto Plaiers is nor vertue, but a heinous vice. The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> would neuer permit ſuch Plaies and acts, for feare leaſt ſome-what might be imprinted in the peoples breſt, contray to the lawes of truth. For as the Apoſtle writeth, <hi>Euillwords corrupt good manners.</hi> And this cauſed the good King Saint <hi>Louis</hi> to baniſh them out of his Court. And in <hi>Caſsiodorus,</hi> King <hi>Theodorick</hi> writeth a long letter to his Prouoſt that he ſhould hinder al ſuch ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles, as corrupted manners and honeſty, rayſing nothing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3558:30"/>but quarrells and contention. The which moued <hi>Aristotle</hi> in his Politicks, to exhort all magiſtrates to forbid ſuch Plaies, and baniſh all vile words out of their City. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth the <hi>Epheſians, that no corrupt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication proceed out of their mouth:</hi> and addeth; <hi>Greene not the holy ſpirit of God, by whom you are ſealed vnto the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. Conſtantinus</hi> the Emperour ordained that no Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhould be admitted to the Table of the Lord. For how can they be partakers of <hi>Chriſts</hi> table and of the table of Diuells. And in the third Counſell of <hi>Carthage, Chap.</hi> 11. And in the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> it was decreed that no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Man or Woman, ſhould reſort to Plaies and Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luds. Wherefore it would be wiſhed that Theaters might be defaced, and no occaſion giuen for ſuch plagues to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter within Cities and houſes, according to the opinion of <hi>Saluianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Marſeilles:</hi> eſteeming all ſuch ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles to be very Apoſtacy, and leauing of the faith of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Chriſtian Religion: and therefore as the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſo great miſchiefe they ought to be ſhunned. Infinite are the ſayings to be alleaged both from Diuine and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane writers againſt Plaies and Enterludes, but I will reſt contented with thoſe few of many that I haue collected. And will now proceed to condemne the vſe of Plaies, by declaring their groſſe abuſe and vnchriſtian impiety.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore they are full of idle and vaine words: of which our Sauiour ſayth,<note place="margin">Scriptures against ſundry vices in Plaies.</note> 
                  <hi>Mathew</hi> 12.26. <hi>I ſay vnto you, of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue account thereof at the day of iudgement.</hi> They are full of obſcaene ſpeeches, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> forbids, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.29. <hi>Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are full of lies and prophane fables: concerning which, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4. Paul <hi>commands</hi> Timothy, <hi>to teach that they giue not heed to fables.</hi> And againe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way prophane, and old Wiues fables: and exerciſe thy ſelfe vnto Godlineſſe:</hi> as if ſuch fables were enemies to Godlineſſe. Againe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4. <hi>O Timotheus keepe that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3558:30"/>vnto thee, and auoid prophane and vaine babling.</hi> Three times in one Epiſtle is the ſame repeated, to ſhew the erneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Paul</hi> in his dehortation. Which leaſt it ſhould not take effect, he againe putteth <hi>Timothy</hi> in minde of it in his ſecond Epiſtle, 2 <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. <hi>verſe. Stay prophane and vaine bablings, for they ſhall increaſe to more vngodlineſſe:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are full of othes, and blaſphemies, curſing, and tearing God and <hi>Chriſt</hi> into as many peeces, as they ſuppoſe there are members in a Man. Againſt which <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. there is the whole third commandement forbidding it.</p>
               <p>They are full of all obſcaenity, acts of Fornication, and practizes of Strumpets and Coſeners, and full of Scurrility, Fooleries, Mocks and Mowes, ſpoken againſt by Saint <hi>Paul Epheſ.</hi> 5.3. <hi>But fornication, and all vncleaneſſe or couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe let it not once be named among you as becommeth Saints: neither filthineſſe, neither fooliſh talking, neither ieſting, which are things vncomely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are full of rayling, reuiling, backbyting, quipping, taunts, and euill ſpeaking, which is forbidden in the ninth commandement. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bare falſe witneſſe.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. writeth that <hi>Raylers ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the kingdome of God,</hi> and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.31. he exhorteth. <hi>Let all bitterneſſe, and anger, and wrath, crying, and euill ſpeaking be put away from you, with all malliciouſneſſe.</hi> This euill tongue <hi>Danid</hi> calleth a ſharpe Razor, and hot burning Coales. Wherevpon <hi>Salomon</hi> in his Prouerbs ſaith. <hi>Hee which keepeth his tongue, keepeth his life.</hi> And herevpon all kinde of mockery, (with which Plaies are enricht,) ought to be ſhunned, which is a reproch couered with ſome fault, and which accuſtometh the mocker to Raile and Lye: and moueth more then an iniury, when it proceedeth from a will to outrage, and a malice without neceſſity: which hath moued ſome to term it an artificiall iniury. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. Willeth vs not ſo much as to Eate and Drink with Raylers, and <hi>Salomon</hi> writeth in his Prouerbes, That God doth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor all Mockers. For this cauſe wee are to reſemble the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3558:31"/>Phiſitians which <hi>Hypocrates</hi> made to ſweare, that they ſhould not bewray the ſecret and hidden falts and euills: or rather follow the counſell of ſaint <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>That laying a ſide all malliciouſneſſe, and all guile, and diſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, and enuy, and all euil ſpeaking, as new borne babes we deſire the ſincere milke of the word, that we may grow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</hi> But now to examine plaies according to the foure gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſes, the <hi>Efficient, Materiall, Formall, and Fynall</hi> cauſe of all things, all men ſhal ſee the goodneſſe that they containe in them: or much rather the great euill wherewith they abound.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Efficient cauſe of Plaies.</note>The <hi>Efficient</hi> cauſe of Playes I haue allready ſhewed in ſundry places of this worke to be the Diuell, chiefely by his owne command, and ſecondarily heretofore by his heatheniſh agents, firſt the Idolatrous <hi>Greekes,</hi> and after the pagane <hi>Romaines,</hi> and at preſent by his Miniſters, the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt-heatheniſh Poets. Wherefore I will inſiſt no longer heerein.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Materiall cauſe of Plaies.</note>The <hi>Materiall</hi> cauſe or matter of Playes is their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect wherevpon they ſpeake and entreat, and that is two fould, either <hi>Diuine</hi> or <hi>Prophane.</hi> If Playes be of <hi>Diuine</hi> matter, then are they moſt intolerable, or rather Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious: for that the ſacred Word of god is to be handled reuerently, grauely, and ſagely, with veneration to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious maieſty of God: and not with ſcoffes and iybes, or with the ieſts of a Foole, as it is in enterludes without any worſhip or reuerence to the ſame. The word of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the price of Chriſts blood, the merrits of his life and paſſion, the holy Scriptures, were not giuen to be abuſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acted on a Stage, but to be Preached by his Godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; it was not giuen to be mixed and interlaced with ſcurrilous and vncomely geſtures, laughters, and vaine lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, but to be grauely handled, and with veneration ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in Gods aſſembly. In <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. it is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ad nothing, nor take away ought from Gods word: to the doers of which in the end of <hi>Iohns Reuelation</hi> there
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3558:31"/>is added a greeuous curſe. Wherefore whoſoeuer abuſeth the word of God on Stages in Playes and Entertludes, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Maieſty of God which ſhineth in the ſame, and maketh a mocking ſtock of him, and thereby purchaſeth iudgement to himſelf. And no maruel, for the ſacred word of God &amp; God himſelfe, is neuer to be thought on, or once named, but in Feare and Reuerence to the ſame. All the whole company of Heauen, Angells, Archangells, Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin, Seraphin, Thrones, Dominations, Virtues, Principalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Poteſtates, and all powers whatſoeuer, yea the Diuells themſelues doe tremble and quake at the naming of God, and at his preſence: And doe theſe mockers and flouters of his Maieſty, theſe diſſembling <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> thinke to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape vnpuniſhed. Beware therefore you Players,<note place="margin">warning to Players.</note> 
                  <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites,</hi> and like good coumptiſts caſt vp your accounts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, what will be your reward in the end. Abuſe God no more, corrupt his people no longer with your dregs, and entermingle not his bleſſed Word with your prophane va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities.</p>
               <p>For in noe wiſe is it lawfull to mixe Scurrility with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity, nor Diuinity with Scurrility. <hi>Theopompus</hi> ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Moſes</hi> Law with his writings and was therefore ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Mad. <hi>Theodictes</hi> began the like practiſe, and the Lord ſtrocke him Blinde. And many others attempting the like deuiſes were all confounded, and died miſerably: beſides which, what is their iudgement in the other world, the Lord onely knoweth.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, if the matter of playes be prophane, then tend they to the diſhonour of God, and nouriſhing of vice, both which are damnable. So that whether they be diuine or prophane, they are quite contrary to the word of grace, and ſucked out of the Diuils teates to nouriſh vs in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, heathenry, and ſinne. To diſcribe the matter of prophaine playes, wee are to conſider the generall kindes of Playes, which is the <hi>Tragedy,</hi> and the <hi>Comedy.</hi> The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3558:32"/>of <hi>Tragedies</hi> is haughtineſſe, arrogancy, ambition, pride, iniury, anger, wrath, enuy, hatred, contention, warre, murther, cruelty, rapine, inceſt, rouings, depredations, piracyes, ſpoyles, roberies, rebellions, treaſons, killing, hewing, ſtabbing, dagger-drawing, fighting, butchery, trechery, villany &amp;c. and all kind of heroyick cuils whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. Of <hi>Comedies</hi> the matter is loue, luſt, lechery, baudry, ſcortation, adultery, vncleanneſſe, pollution, wantonneſſe, chambring, courting, ieaſting, mocking, flouting, foole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, venery drabbery, knauery, coſenage, cheating, hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy, flattery, and the like. And as complements and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants to both kindes of playes is ſwearing, curſing, othes, and blaſphemies, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Hence ariſeth the formall cauſe, or forme of playes, which conſiſteth in the action, and in the Actors.<note place="margin">The formall cauſe of Plaies.</note> The action is two-fould, in word, and in deede. The action in word is laſciuious ſpeches, idle and vaine ſcoffing, ieaſting, and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, and coſenage, knauery, flattery, and what ſoeuer els, ſet forth in their coullors, phraſes, and tearmes, and with the grace, elegancy, and luſtre of the tongue. The action in deede is the ſetting forth of all enormities, and exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, with the perſonating of the doers of them; with falſe repreſentations, lying ſhewes, killing, ſtabbing, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and fighting; actiue demonſtration of coſenage, whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh enticeing, all kinde of villany, and hypocriſie; with embracing, clipping, culling, dandling kiſſing; all manner wanton geſtures, and the like. The forme that conſiſts in the Actors, is the parts they play: And theſe are ioyntly both in Tragedies and Comedies. Tiranous Kinges and Queenes; ambitious Potentates, Nobles, Peeres; vniuſt Iudges, Magiſtrates, Officers, couetous Cittizens, ſpend-all Gentlemen, Gods, Goddeſſes, Fiendes, Furies, Diuells, Hagges, Ghoſts, Witches, Magitians, Sorcerers, Trechers, Murtherers, Swaggerers, Knaues, Drabs, Queans, Whores, Baudes, Courtezans, Rogues, Villaines. Vagsbonds, Theeues, Rouers, Pyrates, Coſoners, Cheaters, Brokers,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3558:32"/>Banckrupts, Hyppocrites, Sycophants, Paraſites, Flatterers, Talecarriers, Makebates, Lecherous old men, Amarous young men, Wanton maides, Laſciuious dames, Vnhoneſt wiues; Rebells, Traytors, proud, hauty, arrogant, inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wicked perſons; Whoremaſters, Gluttons, Drunkards, Spend-thrifts, Fooles, Madmen, Ieſters, Iybers, Flouters, Mockers; and finally contemners of God, his lawes, and the Kinges, and blaſphemers of his holy name; with ſuch like of infinite variety. That if there were nothing els but this, it were ſufficient to withdraw a good Chriſtian from beholding of them. For as often as they goe to Theaters to ſee Playes, they enter into <hi>Venus Pallace</hi> and <hi>Sathans Synagogue,</hi> to betray and inſnare their owne ſouſes. And therefore theſe Players, through the parts they act carrying the note and brand of all kinde of curſed people on their backs, whereſoeuer they goe, are to bee hiſſed out of all Chriſtian Kingdomes, if they will haue truth and not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>Christ</hi> and not the Diuell to dwell among them. The finall cauſe or end of Playes particulerly toucheth their vſe and qualities, wherein I am to anſwer three maine obiections.<note place="margin">The Finall cauſe of Plaies The firſt obie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt obiection is, that they inſtruct men what vices to auoid, what ordinances to obſerue, what enormities to abandon, &amp; what vertues to imbrace. Which M.<hi>Actor</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to bee the finall cauſe why the Greekes admitted Playes in their common-wealth, and which I promiſed in my firſt Book particulerly to anſwer and refute. Therefore let him know that God onely gaue authority of publique inſtruction and correction but to two ſorts of men: to his Eccleſtaſticall Miniſters, and temporal Magiſtrates: hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer inſtituted a third authority of Players, or ordained that they ſhould ſerue in his Miniſtry: and therefore are they to bee reiected with their vſe and quality. As concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Miniſteriall vſe, God requireth no ſuch thing at their hands, that they ſhould take it vpon them: But it is the Diuells craft who ſometimes will change himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3558:33"/>an Angell of Light, that is will colourably ſeeme to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to good, when his intention is to ſeduce, inſnare, and intrappe ſily ſoules in inexplicable euills. But what God doth not require them to doe is performed according to the prauity of their owne nature, and not his wil. And it is a horrible abhomination for thoſe (whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath not put into his Vineyard) to preſume to bee labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers therein. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> will haue none, but whom himſelfe through his holy ſpirit ſhall ſanctifie for that end. And therefore <hi>Luke</hi> 10.2. he teacheth vs to pray <hi>the Lord of the harneſt</hi> (which is himſelfe) <hi>to ſend forth labourers into his harueſt.</hi> Shall wee then pray him to ſend forth Players: no they belong no to his publique miniſtry. God gaue autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to inſtruct and preach, to correct and anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, which is the keyes of heauen, onely to the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors, and not to Players; For it is vnlawfull to caſt pearles before Swine. The Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt take the word of God in their mouthes, and therewith im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, rebuke, and exhort; and may Players doe ſo? no it were moſt impious, as I haue ſhewed before, to mixe Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with ſcurrility on the ſtage. As concerning publique Magiſtracy, Players haue no authority in their enterludes: they haue no law to cauſe men to fly that which is euill, and to follow that which is good. Magiſtrates are ſent of God, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. for the puniſhment of euill doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well. And as the Miniſtry is, ſo is the Magiſtracy the ordinance of God; to which he hath added the good lawes for inſtruction &amp; the ſword for correction. But hath God inſtituted any ſuch authority and liberty to Players? no; for <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>There is no power but of God, and the powers that be ordained of God.</hi> But Playes were ordained by, &amp; dedicated to the Diuell, which is enemy to God and al goodnes. And ful ſory would he be that any (as neuer yet any did) ſhould benefit by a Play: for if he could haue but thought ſo, he would neuer at firſt hau e inſtituted them.</p>
               <p>And ſo to conclude Players aſſume an vnlawfull office to themſelues of inſtruction and correction: and therefore it
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3558:33"/>becometh ſin vnto them, becauſe God neuer ordained them vnto it, which is the reaſon that neuer any profited in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes but in wickednes by them. This is ſufficient to refute the firſt obiection. But becauſe this opinion of the vſe of playes was but the ſuppoſition of the heathen Greeks I will further conuince it with the authority &amp; reaſons of an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then man,<note place="margin">Affricanus in Ciceronem de republica.</note>, ſpeaking of the licentious liberty of Poets and Players tongues, ſaith thus: <hi>Whom did not the Poet touch, nay whom did he not vexe, whom ſpared he? Perhaps</hi> ſaith one, <hi>he quipt a ſorte of wicked, vulgar, ſeditious fellowes, as were</hi> Cleo, Clitophon <hi>and</hi> Hyperbolus: <hi>but it were fitter for ſuch faults to be taxed by the Cenſor, then by the Poet. And it was no more decent that</hi> Pericles <hi>ſhould be ſnuffed at, hauing many yeares gouerned the Citty ſo well, both in peace and warre, then for our</hi> Plautus <hi>or</hi> Naeuius <hi>to deride</hi> Publius <hi>or</hi> Cneius Scipio, <hi>or for</hi> Caecilius <hi>to mock</hi> Marcus Cato. Heere hee ſhewes that not onely the euill, but the good alſo are ſubiect to the bitter mallice of Comedians, worthy therefore to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected. And againe a little after ſaith hee. <hi>Our</hi> 12. <hi>Tables hauing ordained but a very few thinges vppon paine of death, yet thought it good to eſtabliſh this for one of thoſe few; that none ſhould write or act any verſe derogatiue to the good name of any one, or preiudiciall vnto manners. Excellently well; For our liues ought not to bee the ſubiects for Poets to play vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, but for lawfull Magiſtracy, &amp; throughly informed iuſtice to iudge vpon.</hi> Hee proceedeth further in his diſcourſe, and in fine concludeth thus, <hi>That the ancient Romans diſliked that any should be either praiſed or diſpraiſed vpon the ſtage.</hi> This now is wholy enough to confound the firſt, and grand cheefe obiection. For firſt it ſhewes the licenciouſneſſe of Poets pennes, and Players tongues in nipping at men both good and bad; And that ſuch faultes as are reprehended on the ſtage, were better to bee taxed by the Cenſor; And that the ancient Romans <hi>capitis diminutione</hi> made a law to repreſſe the leudnes of Poets and ſtagerits: becauſe the law it ſelfe were ſufficient by the power of Magiſtracy to plant vertue, and iuſtice it ſelfe of ſufficient force to root out vice.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3558:34"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond Obiection.</note>The ſecond obiection is the vulgar opinion of <hi>Actors,</hi> and the moſt part of their prophane auditors, ſome whereof I haue euen heard with mine owne cares to pronounce and affirme: Plaies to be as good, or may doe as much good, as Sermons are,<note place="margin">Jf Plaies do ſo much good, why are they not ſuffered on the Sabbath, a day ſelect wherein to doe good.</note> or may doe. Oh blaſphemy intollerable! Are obſcaene Plaies, and filthy Enterludes comparable to the word of God, the food of life, and life it ſelfe? It is all one as if they had ſaid, Baudry, Heathenry, Paganiſme, Scurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and Diuelry, it ſelfe is equall with Gods Word: Or that <hi>Sathan</hi> is equipolent with the Lord. God hath ordayned his bleſſed word, and made it the ordinary meanes of our Saluation: the Diuell hath inferred the other as the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meanes of our deſtruction. God hath ſet his holy Word and Miniſters to inſtruct vs in the way of Life: the Diuell inſtituted Plaies and Actors to ſeduce vs into the way of Death: and will they yet compare the one with the other? If he be accurſed that calleth Light Darkneſſe, and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Light; Truth Falſhood, and Falſhood Truth; then <hi>a fortieri,</hi> is he accurſed that ſaith Plaies and Enterludes are Equiualent with Sermons, or compareth Comedies and Tragedies to the Word of God, whereas there is no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, almoſt, which they maintaine not. For doe they not nouriſh Idleneſſe? and <hi>Otia dant Vitia.</hi> Idleneſſe is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Vice, and many vitious Perſons when they know not how any longer to be idle, for variety of Idleneſſe goe to ſee Plaies. Doe they not draw the people from hearing the Word of God, and Godly Lectures? For you ſhall haue them flock thick and three-fould to the Play-houſes, and withall Celerity make ſpeed to enter in them, leaſt they ſhould not get place neere enough vnto the Stage (ſo prone and ready are they to euill;) when the Temple of God ſhall remaine bare and empty.<note place="margin">The Play-houſe full, but the Church empty.</note> And thoſe that will neuer come at Sermons will flow thither apace: the reaſon is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the way that leadeth to life is Narrow, and few that tread that Path: but the way that leadeth to deſtruction is Brode, and many finde it. And this ſheweth they are not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3558:34"/>of God, who refuſe to heere his word: but of the Diuell whoſe exerciſes they goe to viſite. Doe they not teach Cheating and Coſenage, by publiſhing their tricks of Knauery? Doe they not inſtruct in Chambering and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, by ſhewing how to court and congie? Doe they not inſinuate Baudry, Act Foolery, and renew the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Heathen Idolatry? Doe they not induce Whoredome, and vncleaneſſe? nay; are they not rather plaine deuourers of Maidenly Virginity and Chaſtity? For prooſe whereof but marke the madding and running to Theaters and Curtaines, daily and hourely, night and day, time and tyde, too ſee Playes and Enterludes. Where ſuch wanton geſtures, ſuch diſhoneſt ſpeeches, ſuch laughing and flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſuch lipping and kiſſing, ſuch clipping and culling, ſuch luſtfull paſſions, ſuch wincking and glancing of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton eies and the like is vſed, as is wonderful and exceeding ſhamefull to behold.<note place="margin">The fruit of Plaies.</note> Then theſe goodly Pageants being done, euery one ſorteth to his mate, each bring another home-ward of their way: then begin they to repeate the laſciuious acts and ſpeeches they haue heard, and thereby infect their minde with wicked paſſions, ſo that in their ſecret conclaues they play the <hi>Sodomits,</hi> orworſe. And theſe for the moſt part are the fruits of Playes.</p>
               <p>The third obiection is, that many good examples may belearned out of them. And truely ſo there may;<note place="margin">The third Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection what good there is to be learned as Playes.</note> For if you will learne to doe any euill, skilfully, cunningly, couertly, or artificially, you need goe noe other where then to the Theater: If you will learne falſhood if you will learne coſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, if you will learne indirect dealing, if you will learne to deceiue, if you will learne to play the hippocrite, ſico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, Paraſite and flatterer; if you will learne to cogge, lye, and falſifie, if you will learne to ieſt, laugh and fleere, to grinne, nodde, and mow: if you will learne to play the Vice, to curſe, ſweare, teare, and blaſpheme both heauen and earth, in all kindes and diuerſities of othes; if you will learne to play the Baud or courteſan, to polute your ſelfe,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3558:35"/>to deuirginate maides, to defloure wiues, or to rauiſh wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes by inticing them to luſt, if you will learne to drabbe and ſtabbe, to murther, kill, and ſlay, if you will learne to picke, ſteale, rob, and roue, if you will learne to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Princes, cloſely to carry treaſons, to conſume trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, to practiſe idleneſſe, to ſing and talke of filthy loue and venery, if you will learne to deride, quippe, ſcorne, ſcoffe, mock, and flout, to flatter and ſmoth, if you will learne to play the Diuell, the ſwaggerer, the whoremaiſter, the glutton, the drunkard, the iniurious or inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if you will learne to become proud, haughty, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant: Finally if you wil learn to contemne God &amp; all his lawes, to care neither for heauen nor hell, and to commit all kind of ſinne and miſcheefe with ſecreſie and art, you need not goe to any other choole, for all theſe good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples may you ſee painted before your eyes in enterludes and playes. Wherefore that man that giueth mony for the maintenance of them, muſt needs incurre the danger of <hi>praemunire</hi> that is ſcuere iudgement except they repent.<note place="margin">A diuine prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire.</note> For the Apoſtle biddeth vs beware leaſt wee communicate with other mens ſinnes, and this their doing is not onely to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with other mens ſinnes, and maintaine euill to the deſtruction of themſelues and many others, but alſo a maintaining of a great ſort of idle and buzzing drones, to ſucke vp and deuoure the good hony, wherevpon the poore bees ſhould liue. And therefore let all Players and founders of Playes, as they tender the ſaluation of their owne ſoules, and others, leaue off that curſed kind of life, and betake themſelues to ſuch honeſt exerciſes and godly miſteries, as God hath commanded in his word to get their liuing with-all. For who will call him a wiſe man that playeth the foole and the vicer Who can call him a good Chriſtian that play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the part of a Diuell the ſwerne enemy of Chriſt? who can call him a iuſt man that playeth the diſſembling hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite? who can call him a ſtraight dealing man, that playeth a coſoners tricke: and ſo of all the reſt. The wiſe man is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3558:35"/>aſhamed to play the foole, but Players will ſeeme to bee ſuch in publique view to all the world: a good Chriſtian hateth the Diuell; but Players will become artificiall Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelse excellently well: a iuſt man cannot indure hypocriſy; but all the acts of Players is diſſimolation, and the proper name of Player (witneſſe the <hi>Apology</hi> it ſelte) is <hi>hypocrite:</hi> a true dealing man cannot indure deceipt, but Players get their liuing by craft and coſenage. For what greater chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting can there be then for money to render that which is not moneys worth. Then ſeeing they are fooles,<note place="margin">Of what ſort of men Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers bee.</note> artificiall Diuells, hypocrites and coſeners; moſt euident it is that their Artis not for Chriſtians to exerciſe, as being diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall, and themſelues infamous: ſuch indeed as the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians</hi> had, and we alſo haue great reaſon to extrude out of our common wealth, for they are Idle, vicious, ciſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, malitious, peiudiciall and vnprofitable to the ſame. They are Idle, for they can take no paynes, they know not how to worke, nor in any lawfull calling to get their liuing: but to auoid labour and worke, like braue and noble beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, they ſtand to take money of euery one that comes to ſee them loyter and play. Hence it is that they are Vicious; for idleneſſe is the mother of vice, and they cannot exerciſe their offices but in vices, and treating of and with vicious men. They are diſhoneſt; for they get not to eate by doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good works, but by ſpeaking filthy, vile, and diſhoneſt words. They are malicious; for they are accuſtomed, either for their friends or themſelues, when they ioue not a man to ſpeake euill of him: and colourably vnder hand to mock and flout at any. They are preiudiciall and vnprofitable to the common wealth; for they coſen and mock vs with vaine wordes, and wee pay them good mony, But now to draw to the end and concluſion of my diſcourſe, I will but only deſcribe briefely and in few wordes, who for the moſt part they are which runne madding vnto playes. In generall the vulgar ſort, in whom, <hi>Cicero pro Planc.</hi> ſaith <hi>non est concilium, non ratio, non diſcrimen,</hi> there is no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3558:36"/>reaſon, or diſcretion. But to particularize ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt all. The prophane gallant to feed his pleaſure; the Citty dames to laugh at their owne ſhames: the Country Clowne to tell wonders when hee comes home of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities he hath ſeene, the baudes to intice, the whores and courtezans to ſet themſelues to ſale, the cutpurſe to ſteale, the pickpocket to filch, the knaue to be inſtructed in more coſoning trickes, youth to learne amorous conceits, ſome for one wicked purpoſe, ſome for another: none to any good intent, but all fruitleſly to miſpend their time. But among any others that goe to the Theaters, when ſhall you ſee an ancient cittizen, a chaſt matron, a modeſt maid, a graue Senator, a wiſe Magiſtrate, a iuſt Iudge, a godly Preacher, a religious man not blinded in ignorance, but making conſcience of his wayes? you ſhall neuer ſee any of theſe men at Playes, for they count it ſhamefull and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious, euen an act of reproch that may redound vn to them.</p>
               <p>Then to conclude all, ſeeing Playes are the inſtitution of the Diuell himſelfe, and the practize of Heathen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple nouzeled in ignorance: ſeing they took originall from Paganiſme, and were dedicated to their Idol-Gods, as now alſo they are the houſe, ſtage and apparell to <hi>Venus,</hi> the muſicke to <hi>Apollo,</hi> the penning to <hi>Minerua,</hi> the ſongs to the <hi>Muſes,</hi> the action and pronounciation to <hi>Mercury:</hi> ſeeing they are inricht with fables, lies, diſhoneſties and all kind of kanueries: ſeeing the actors of them haue been counted ignominious, and in all ages by the beſt men branded with infamy: ſeeing by the wiſeſt men they haue beene expeld out of their common wealth, and eſteemed as vagabonds, corrupters of good manners, ſubuerters of religion in peoples heartes, and ſeducers of men to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: ſeeing by ſome they haue not beene admitted to the Lords table: ſeeing their action both in word and deed is to be abhord: ſeeing they carry the note &amp; brand of all kind of curſed people on their backs: ſeeing they
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3558:36"/>were neuer ordained of God to giue inſtruction, but by the Diuell to teach lewdnes and diſſolution: ſeeing they are idle drones, and preiudiciall to the common wealth: ſeeing none of the beſt ſort will frequent their theaters for very ſhame: ſeeing the theater is Sathans Synagogue and the diuells owne houſe: ſeeing Playes haue beene condemned by Pagans and Chriſtians, by Synods and Counſells, by ancient Fathers and late Writers, by both the old and new Teſtament: ſeeing their ſubiect and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is nothing but filthineſſe and villany: ſeeing they are full of abuſes, againſt which ſundry places of Scripture do teſtifye: ſeeing from them can bee learned no good, but any cuill that wickednes can deſire. Then doe I earneſtly intreat cuery one, as they loue their owne ſoules, to deteſt and abandon them. As for thoſe which will yet remaine in blindneſle, or preſume to go to Sathans Sanctuary, in hope there to learne any good, let them conſider in how palpable darkeneſle they wander, while they forſake the truth and cleaue to fables, like vnto whom the Apoſtle mentioneth ſome in his 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. where hee thus exhorteth. <hi>Timothy. Preach the word, bee inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, improue, rebuke, exhort, with all long ſuffering and doctrine. For the time will come when they will not ſuffer wholſome Doctine, but hauing their eares itching, ſhall after their owne luſtes get them a heape of teachers, and ſhall turne their eares from the truth and be giuen vnto fables.</hi> And finally let me intreat eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one that will reclaime themſelues from Playes, for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and execution of their good thought and intention, to be are this Sermon of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in their mind. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>This I ſay and teſtifie in the Lord, that yee henceforth wallke not as other Gentiles walke, in vanity of their mind, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their cogitation darkened, and beeing ſtrangers from the life of God through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the bardnes of their heart, who being past feeling haue giuen themſelues vnto wantonnes, to worke all vncleannes enen with
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3558:37"/>greedines. But yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Chriſt. <hi>If ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ard him and haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> taught by him, as the truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Ieſus <hi>that yee caſt off (concerning the conuerſation in times juſt the old man, which is corrupt through the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>aue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble luſtes: and be renewed in the Spirit of your mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>— Fides ab pudes eſſe Poeta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sinugis opus eſt pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilibus inſeruire,</l>
                  <l>Et iucunda ſequi ſpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>dacia vere.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:37"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:38"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3558:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
